<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[The perfect pathway to salvation]</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 174 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20579.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112957</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848198</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848198</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1639:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[The perfect pathway to salvation]</title>
                  <author>R., James (James Rowbotham), attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[348] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Orwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By James Rowbotham?--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Title and imprint information suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>With prayers at end for Queen Elizabeth.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-X Y⁶.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:1"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hrough two fieldes, Christian Reader, the way is directed: the one full of Briers, hath the perfest Path to Saluation, the other (more pleaſant to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious minde) leades to endleſſe miſorie: church with aduice, and ſhun with diſcretion. And to me thy vnknown frtend, lend (I pray thee) us friendly iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as I ſhall wiſh for thy proſporous estate: farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="calendar">
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:2"/>
            <div type="month">
               <head>Januarie hath 31. daies. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>10.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>14.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>The Cyrcumciſion of Christ.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">On which day Noe being in the Arke vpon the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, began to ſee the tops of the high Mountaines.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>The Epiphany.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 10. day, Nabuchado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nozor, aſsieged noce againe Ieruſalem, 2. King. 15.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">The 11. day, Noe, fortie dayes after he had ſeene the toppes of the Mountaines, ſent out the Rauen, and after that the Doue, which retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, Gen. 8.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">Ezechias, in his extreme
<pb facs="tcp:13277:2"/>ſicknes, was healed by God, his life was prolonged by 15. yeares.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">The Sunne to the wonder of all the world, returned his courſe backward by 10. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. 4. King. 20. Eſd. 38.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>The midde vvinter.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>The conuerſion of S. Paul.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">Iacob fled fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his brother Eſau, &amp; we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to his vnckle La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban, where after 7. yeares, he maried Lea and Rachel, &amp; by them, and their handmayds had the 12. Patriarks. Gen. 29</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:3"/>
               <head>Februarie hath <hi>28.</hi> daies. The Moone <hi>29:</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>10.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>14.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>The purification of Mary.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">The holy man Iohn the Baptiſt, being ſent of God as a meſſenger, or tidings brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of our health and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, began to prepare the way, againſt the comming of Chriſt. Mark. 1.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">Our Sauiour and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ieſus Chriſt, after he was Baptiſed of Iohn in Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan, began to preach, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:3"/>ſpread abroade the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God. Mark. 1.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 18. day, Noe put out once again the Doue, which brought an Olyue branch.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>S. Matthy Apos<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The Doue was ſent the third time, and returned no more to Noe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:4"/>
               <head>March hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>12.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>12.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">The third day, the temple of leruſalem was wholy fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, &amp; conſecrated. 1. Eſd. 6. And that was 500. and 15. yeares before the birth of our Lord,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">The tenth day, Chriſt was on the other ſide of Iordan, where he was aduertiſed of Lazarus ſickneſſe.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 13. day, the Faſt of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was celebrated, becauſe that day was appointed, to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:4"/>pat the lewes to death. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. 3.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 16. day, Lazarus was rayſed vp againe. Iohn. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 20. day, Chriſt made his entrance into Ieruſalem.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 24. day, he made his Supper, and was taken.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>The annunciation of Mary.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell>The 25. day, was crucified</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 26. day, he reſted in the Sepulchre.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 27. day, he roſe again from death.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:5"/>
               <head>Aprill hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>29.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>13.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>11.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>Noe vncouered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ark. Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The Tabernacle was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by Moſes Exod. 40.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">Ieſus Chriſt, the 8. day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his reſurrection, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe to the Apoſtles, which were affembled where S. Thomas was preſent.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 10. the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael went ouer Iordan drie footed. Ioſ 34.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">The 13. day, Aſſuerus gaue out proclamation, 10 put all the lewes within his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to death. Heſter. 3.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 14. day, was the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration
<pb facs="tcp:13277:5"/>of the Paſſeouer.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 15. day, the people came our of Aegypt. Exo. 12.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">The 18. day, the people went ouer the red Sea drye footed, and Pharao was drowned with all his hoaſt.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>S. Marke Euangelist.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 22. day, the people came to Mara, the waters wherof of they could not drink, wherefore they murmured. Exod. 5.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:6"/>
               <head>May hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>16.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>8.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Philip and Jacob.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The Aſcenſion of Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, fortie dayes after his reſurrection. Matth. 16.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">God commaunded Noe to carrie victuals into the Arke, Gen. 6.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Terme beginneth.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">They which haue not ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated the Paſſcouer in the firſt moneth, did cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the 14. day, Num. 19.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 14. Ezechias did firſt ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebtate the Paſſeouer. Par. 30</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 15. the Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael murmured after fleſh, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:13277:6"/>God ſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty of quailes This was the 30 day after the departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegypt. Exo. 16</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 16. God made Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na to raine downe. Exo. 16.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 17. day, Noe entred into the Arke, Gen. 7.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 20. day, the people departed from mount Sina. Numb. 9.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 22. day, fire from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, conſumed a part of the hoaſt of Iſrael. Num. 12.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The 27. day, Noe came forth of the Arke.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:7"/>
               <head>June hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>16.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>8.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">This day this children of Iſrael came to mount Sina, and went thence the third moneth, where they taried almoſt a yeare. Exod. 9.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">The 6. day, the temple of Diana in Epheſus was bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the yeare before Ieſus Chriſt, 54. which temple was accounted the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent of all the heathen Churches.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13277:7"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">The 23. day of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, King Aſſuerus gaue out Proclamation in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the Iewes, againſt Haman and his conſpiracie. Heſter. 8.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>S. John Baptist.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The Arke of Noe was lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp this day by the waters of the flood. Gen. 8.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>S. Peter the Apostle.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:8"/>
               <head>July hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>15.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>9.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 9. of this moneth, the citie of leruſalem was aſsie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the ſpace of 18, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, was finally take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the King of Babylon. Ierem. 39.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Dogge dayes beginneth.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="13">The 50. day, after that the Iſraelites were thus departed and were come to the mount of Sinay, the lawe of the ten Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements was to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> giuen by almighty God, with a great and terrible magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, at which time alſo God gaue to them certaine
<pb facs="tcp:13277:8"/>polnike gouernande, &amp; a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall kingdome, in which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing wanted, that appertai ned to the true worſhipping.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Mary Magdalen.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>S. Iames the Apostle.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">Of God and of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt in time to come ſhould be borne. So that among his people alway remayned the Church, and the true word of God, vntill after Chriſt had ſuffered. Exod. 19. &amp; 20.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:9"/>
               <head>August hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>14.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>10.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">Aaron dyed in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine of Hor, being 1 2 3. yeares olde, 40. yeares after the comming out of Aegypt. Numb. 20. and 33.38.39.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="8">The ſame day Eſdras en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into leruſalem, with a compame of lewes, and was receiued by thoſe, which 80. yeares before, hee went vp thither with Zorobal el, the yeare before the comming of leſus Chriſt. 457. Eſd. 7.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">The 10. day, the Pemple of Ieruſalem was ſet on fire by the Souldiers of Titus,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:9"/>and hath not ſince bin buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againe, Ioſephus lib. 6. chap. 26.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Dogge dayes end.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Bartholmevv Apostle.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">Religion as on this day was reformed, according to Gods expreſſe truth in the moſt renoumed citie of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua. 1535.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:10"/>
               <head>September hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>29.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>12.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>12.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">Suſanna the moſt chaſte matron of the Hebrues, by two falſe Prieſts, was accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of adulterie, but by the poſſicie of young Daniel, ſhe was purged, and the Prieſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the fire. Dan. 13.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="6">The ninth day of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, leruſalem was put to fire and ſworde, and wholy oucrthrowne, as Chriſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told them fortie yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ioſephus. lib. 7. cap. 26.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">Chriſoſtome being cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of his Church of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:10"/>Conſtantinople, as vpon this day dyed.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Saint Matthevv.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 25. Nehemias did fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the repayring the wals of Ieruſalem. Anno 300. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Natiuitie of Chriſt. Nehem. 6.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>Saint Michael.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:11"/>
               <head>October hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>10.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>14.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The Feaſt of Trumpets, commaunded to the Iewes. Leuit. 23.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell rows="2">The Iewes faſted &amp; wept for Gedaliah, Ierem. 47.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Terme beginneth.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">The 10. day, was the feaſt of reconciliation, which was the onely day that God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to faſt.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 15. day, the feaſt of Tabernacles began, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted
<pb facs="tcp:13277:11"/>ſeuen dayes. Leuit. 22.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ S. Luke Euangelist.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 18. day, which was the 150, after the beginning of the flood, the Arke reſted vpon the Mountaine of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarat in Armenia. Gen. 8.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 24. day, Titus gaue forth 3000. Iewes to the wild beaſts. Anno. 73.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Simon and Jude.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:12"/>
               <head>Nouember hath <hi>30.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>29.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>9.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>15.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ All Saints.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">The Emperour Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus, ſonne of Conſtantine, dyed this day 364, after the Natiuitie of Ieſus Chriſt.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">The 10. day happened the wofull ſlaughter of Verna, where Ladiſſan king of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary was ſlaine by the Turk, ann. 1445. Alſo as vpon this daye. Martin Luther was borne.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell rows="12">The 15. day was the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite Feaſt by Ieroboam, after he had withdrawn the ten tribes of Iſrael, from the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:12"/>obedience of Roboam their lawfull King, which he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained in Dan and Bethel, after he had ſet vp the gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den Calues, to the intent the people ſhould goe no more to worſhip in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. 3. King. 22.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">The 17. day of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, Queene Elizabeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan her raigne.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Terme endeth.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ S And<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>evv Apostle.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:13"/>
               <head>December hath <hi>31.</hi> dayes. The Moone <hi>30.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">The day is <hi>8.</hi> houres. The night is <hi>16.</hi> houres.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Shortest day.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell rows="5">The 15. the yeare before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> natiuity of Chriſt, 145. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus the great, ſet vp an idoll vpon the Altar of the Lord in Ieruſalem. 1. Mach. 1</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13277:13"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell> </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>21</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Saint Thomas Apostle.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>22</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">Saint Iohn Euangeliſt died in Epheſus, being of the age of 89. yeares, vnder Traian</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>b</cell>
                        <cell>¶ <hi>The Natiuitie of Christ.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>c</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Saint Stephen Martyr.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>d</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Saint John Euangelis<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>28</cell>
                        <cell>e</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>¶ Jnnocents day.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>f</cell>
                        <cell rows="3">the Emperour, about thirtie yeares after the deſtruction of Ieruſalem.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>30</cell>
                        <cell>g</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>31</cell>
                        <cell>A</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="rule">
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:14"/>
            <head>A rule to knowe, when the Termes beginneth and endeth.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Hillarie Terme beginneth the</hi> 23. <hi>day of Januarie, if it be not Sunday, then the next day after: and endeth the</hi> 12. <hi>of Februarie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Easter Terme beginneth</hi> 18. <hi>daies after Easter, and endeth foure dayes after the Aſcention day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trinitie Terme beginneth the next day after Corpus Christy day, and endeth the vvedneſday, foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene dayes after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michaelmaſſe Terme beginneth the</hi> 10. <hi>day of October, if it be not Sunday, and endeth the</hi> 28. <hi>day of Nouember.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table">
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:14"/>
            <head>The degrees of Mariage.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>No man may marrie his Grandmother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Grandfathers wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues grandmother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers ſiſter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers ſiſter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers brothers wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers brothers wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues fathers ſiſter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues mothers ſiſter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Mother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Stepmother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues mother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:15"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>No woman ought to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie her Grandfather.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Grandmothers husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands grandfather.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Fathers ſiſters husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Mothers ſiſters husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands fathers brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands mothers brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con</cell>
                     <cell>Father.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Stepſather.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands father.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con</cell>
                     <cell>Sonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:15"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>No man may marrie his Siſter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues ſiſter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes ſonnes wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters ſonnes wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wines ſonnes daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wines daughters daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con</cell>
                     <cell>Biſters daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers ſonnes wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters ſonnes wife.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wines brothers daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Wiues ſiſters daughter.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:16"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>No woman ought to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie her brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands brother.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughters ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Sonnes daughters husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Daughter daughters husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands ſonnes ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands daughters ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>con.</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers daughters husband</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Siſters daughters husband.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Husbands daughters ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>af.</cell>
                     <cell>Brothers ſiſters ſonne.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:16"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How a man ſhall behaue himſelfe in the Morning when he riſeth.</head>
               <p>When thou riſeſt in the morning, looke that thou with all humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mind, kneele downe, and lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp thy hart. thy hands, &amp; thine eyes into heauen, vnto God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almighty, pray on this maner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Mcrning.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Almghty and moſt grntle God, wre thanke thee for that ſweet ſleepe and comfortable reſt that thou haſt gruen vs this night. And foraſnitich as thou haſt commanded by thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:17"/>holy word, that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould he idle, but alwaies occupied in vertuous exerciſes, euery man according to his callin.g We moſt humblie beſeech thee, that thine eyes may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vpon vs, daily defend vs in forrow, ſuccour vs, che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſh, comfort, and gouerne all our counſailes, ſtudies, and labours. In ſuch wiſe, that we may ſo ſpend this day, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy moſt bleſſed will, without hurting of our neighbour, that we may dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb facs="tcp:13277:17"/>and warely eſchue, and audide all things that ſhould diſpleaſe thee, ſe thtem al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies before our eyes, liue in thy feare, and euer worke that that may be found accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table before thy diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, vnto the praiſe of thy holy name, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So be it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After thou haſt prayed on this maner (ſeeing that we be all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerse) it ſhall be expedient (if thou haſt conuenient leiſure thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) to confeſſe thy ſelfe on this maner, vnto God the father.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="confession">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:18"/>
               <head>The confeſſion of our ſinnes vnto God the father.</head>
               <p>O Almighty God, and he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of heauen &amp; earth I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe my ſelfe vnto thee, euen from the very hart, that I am a milerable, wretched and abominable ſinner. And haue wickedly tranſgreſſed all thy holy commandements, &amp; the druine precepts of thy godlie will. The ſins (alas) which I haue committed in my fleſh againſt thee, are ſo great, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:18"/>ſo exceedingly increaſed, that they are no leſſe innumerable the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſands of the Sea: and they thruſt me down, euen as an intollerable burthen. In theſe wicked ſinnes (oh Lord God) haue I hitherto wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will of the Prince of this world, whiles I did that was pleaſant to the fleſhand ill luſts, through baine thoughts, the blindnes of the heart, the outward pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of godlines, and fayned faith. This came to paſſe (oh
<pb facs="tcp:13277:19"/>wretch that I am) becauſe that I did neuer earneſtlie ſtriue againſt the ſuggeſtions of Sathan, nor the concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences or deſires of the world, nor yet the luſtes of the fleſh. But filthily obeyed them a thouſand times more then the motions of thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, O Lorde my God. It came to paſſe alſo, that I did ſet naught by thy godly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, deſpiſed thy holy name, and feaed thy bengeance and heauy viſpleaſure nothing at
<pb facs="tcp:13277:19"/>all. But whatſoeuer I haue in this behalfe offended thy moſt godly maieſtie, it ſore repenteth me, and the fault grieueth me, euen vnto the very hart. And if it were not (O moſt mercifull Father) that thou hadſt layd vp mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the bowels, blood, and wounds of Ieſus Chriſt thy Sonne, and or Lord, for ſo many as vnfeinedly repent, and truely beleeue, be their ſins neuer ſo great &amp; many, I ſhould ſee no other way,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:20"/>but throwe my ſelfe downe headlong through deſpecati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, into the bottomeies pit of hell. But foraſmuch as thou haſt ſet thy welbeloned Son Ieſus Chriſt, to be our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator and mercie ſtocke and haſt promiſed grace, mercie, and forgiueneſſe of ſins, to as many as aſke it in his name, through faith in his bloood. Therefore, in this time of grace &amp; mercy, I miſerable ſinner come now vnto thee, and deſire thee my Lord God,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:20"/>that thou wilt graund mee through that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, a right &amp; true ſaith. And for his lake forgiue me all my ſins, and make me to walke daily more and more in a newe heart, and in the fruits of the holy Ghoſt, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I may vtterl deſpiſe all the vngodly luſtes of this world, and that I may be found con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ent, pure of liuing, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, good, righteous, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, diligent in all goodneſſe, meeke, mercifull, modeſt,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:21"/>humble, and ready to forgiue ſuch as offend me euen from the very hart. And ſo liue all the daies of my life, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy diuine will, and true feare: that I may dye to the world, to all ſinne, and to my ſelfe. And with a good confience, and merrie heart, looke for the comming of the Lord and my Sauiour, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. To whom with thee and the holy Ghoſt, be all honour and glorie, for euer and euer. So be it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:21"/>
                  <hi>Thou maiſt (if thou wilt) after thy confeſſion, ſay the Lordes prayer. And ſo commending thy ſelfe vnto God, fall to ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and vertuous exerciſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy calling, but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thou doet, doe it with pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and with ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of eye. Yea, ſo doe it, as though God were preſent and looked vpon thee, as vndoubtedly he doth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VVhen thou goeſt to thy labour or vvorke.</head>
               <p>O Moſt kinde and gentle heauenly Father, thou knoweſt and haſt alſo taught
<pb facs="tcp:13277:22"/>vs, how great the weakeneſſe of man is, ſo that no man (without thy good helpe) can do any thing. Thus bouchſafe to ſend vs thy holy ſpirit, that he may ſtrengthen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and moue our vnderſtanding and reaſon in all things, that we this day outwardly ſhall goe about and take in hand, or of that we inwardly ſhal thinke or haue in minde, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that it may all be done to his glorie, and to the profite of our neighbour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:22"/>
               <head>A Prayer for the Euening.</head>
               <p>O Lord God, Father euer laſting and full of pittie, wee acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that we be not worthie to lift vp our eyes to heauen, much leſſe to preſent our ſelues before thy diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtie with confidence that thou wilt heare our prayers and graunt one requeſts, if we conſider our owne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aings. For our conſciences doe accuſe vs, and our ſinnes witneſſe againſt vs, and we
<pb facs="tcp:13277:23"/>know that thou art an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iudge, which doeſt not iuſtifie the ſinnerse &amp; wicked men, but puniſheſt the faults of all ſuch as tranſgreſſe thy commandements. Yet moſt mercifull father, ſince it hath pleaſed thee to command vs to call vpon thee in all our troubles and aduerſities, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing euen then to helpe vs, when we feele our ſelues, as it were ſwal owed vp of death and deſperation: we vtterly renounce all worldly
<pb facs="tcp:13277:23"/>confidence, and flee to thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne goodneſſe, as our onely ſtay and refuge, beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thee not to cal to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berance our mauifold ſinnes and wickednes, whereby we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually prouoke thy wrath and indignation againſt vs: neither our negligence and wickedneſſe, which haue nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worthely eſteemed, nor in our liues ſufficiently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed the ſweete comfort of the Goſpell reuealed vnto vs: but rather to accept the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:24"/>obedience and death of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, who by offering vp his body in ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiee once for all, hath made a ſufficient recompence for all our ſins. Haue mercie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpon vs. O Lord, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our offences. &amp; each vs by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly ſpirit, that we may rightly weigh them, and earneſtly repent for the ſame: and ſo much the rather, O Lord, becauſe that the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate and ſuch as thou haſt forſaken, cannot praiſe thee,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:24"/>nor call vpon thy name, but the repenting heart, the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull mind, the conſcience oppreſſed, hungring and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting for thy grace ſhall euer ſet forth thy praiſe and glory. And albeit we be but worms &amp; duſt, yet thou art our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and we be the workes of thy hands: yea, thou art our redeemer, and we be the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whom thou haſt bought: thou art our God, and we thine inheritance. Correct vs not therefore in thine anger
<pb facs="tcp:13277:25"/>O Lord) neither according to our deſarts puniſh vs, but mercifully chaſtiſe vs with a fatherly affection, that all the world may knowe, that at what time ſo euer a Sinner doth repent him of his ſinne from the bottome of his hart, thou wilt put away all his wickednes out of thy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance as thou haſt promiſed by thy holy Prophets.</p>
               <p>Finally, foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed thée, to make the night for man to reſt in, as
<pb facs="tcp:13277:25"/>thou haſt ordeyned him the day to trauaile: graunt (O deare Father) that we may ſo take our bodily reſt, that our ſoules may continuallie watch for the time, that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare for our deliuerance out of this mortall life, and in the me and ſeaſon, that we be not ouercome by any ſautaſies, dreames, or other temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but fully ſet our mindes vpon thee, loue thee, ſeare thee, and reſt in thee, in ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:13277:26"/>ſorte that our very ſleepe alſo may be to the glorie of thy name. Furthermore, that our ſleepe be not exceſſſiue or ouer much after the inſatiable deſire of the fleſh: but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient to content our weake nature, that we may be better be diſpoſed to liue in all godly conuerſation, to the glorie of thy holy name, and profite of our Brethren, thorow Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, in whoſe name we make our humble petitions
<pb facs="tcp:13277:26"/>vnto thee, as he hath taught vs, ſaying: <hi>Our father which art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Almighty and euerlaſting God, vouchſafe we beſeech thee to grant vs perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in thy liuely faith, augmenting and increaſing the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me in vs daylie, vntill me grow to the full meaſure of our perſectiotn in Chriſt: whereof we make our confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſaying: <hi>I beleene in God the Father almightie &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lorde bleſſe vs and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:27"/>ſaue vs: the Lord make his face to ſhine vpon vs: and be mercifull vnto vs: the Lord turne his fauourable counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance towards vs, and grant vs his peace. The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the loue of God, and the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the holy Ghoſt be with vs and remaine with vs for euer. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VVhen a man is bound to vvarde any iourney.</head>
               <p>THis our life moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord, is nothing els
<pb facs="tcp:13277:27"/>but a pilgrimage &amp; through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare: for we haue here no abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or dwelling place. We are come from thee, and we muſt returne againe vnto thee. But amongſt or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene all the traps aſſaults, pits, and ſnares which the Diuell hath layde out, and ſpread abroad for vs, blinded in ſinne: Vouchſafe thou, O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, to leade vs with thy right hand, for thou art a true, truſtie, and a ſure friend. Open our
<pb facs="tcp:13277:28"/>eyes to the intent that we miſſe not the way, which thou thy ſelfe art, but leade vs through, and by thy ſelfe, vnto thy Father, to the intent that all we may be made one with thee and him, euen like as hou art one with him.</p>
               <p>O moſt mercifull Lorde, like as thou doeſt ſend thine holy Angels to be defenders of as many as ſerue &amp; pleaſe thee with a ſimple, innocent and pure heart, by the which they be led like as young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:28"/>oren, are lead of them which are elder and ſtronger than they. And like as thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt vouchſafe to ſend thine Angell <hi>Raphal</hi> to be a guide vnto the Sonne of that roue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent man <hi>Toby:</hi> Vouchſafe euen ſo (O Lord) to ſend vs the ſame Angell, (although we are not ſo worthie as the ſame <hi>Toby</hi> was) that he may encourage and leade vs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that way, which is not pleaſant vnto vs, but vnto thee. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:29"/>
               <head>A Prayer for a Christian life.</head>
               <p>MOſt mercifull &amp; migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, take away from vs all euill counſell, and then our ſinnes: ſuffer vs not to run into an vngodlie and wicked life, and ſinally, kéepe our minds far from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of godlineſſe, and ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of vertue, and in the ſtead of thoſe euils, graunt that we may continuallie be occupied in thy law and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scriptures, that we be
<pb facs="tcp:13277:29"/>not caried about like the wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, as light duſt, and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les chaffe, with euery blaſt of affection and Docirine, but rather that we as trees plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the water brookes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d with the life of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and faith, may alſo bring foorth the fruites of good workes: and that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer we take in hand may proſper, and tende to thy praiſe, and glorie of thy name and furtherance of our ſaluation: and at the laſt,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:30"/>when the wicked ſhall all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in thy iudgement, we may ſtedfaſily ſtand and be made perfect, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer in distreſſe.</head>
               <p>SEeing that (O almightie God) our wretch edueſh and pouertie is right great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therefore haue we very much neede of thy ſaiuation, for ſe long as we now flee vnto the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the intent thou ſhouldſt be our ſpeedie ſuccour and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red defence, we call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberance
<pb facs="tcp:13277:30"/>our moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinnes, corrupt life, and leaud behauiour, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we wil hide, or yet if we were willing thereto, could keep the ſame ſecret fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee. Thou right well perceiueſt al our naughtines, which we truly acknowledge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnto thy diuine maieſtie: we haue grieuouſlie ſinned, we haue done greatly amiſſe, we haue bin marueilous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient, very ſtubborne, and exceeding wilful againſt thee,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:31"/>who deſerue farre more hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous diſpleaſures, then theſe, which we now feele and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. But bowe thou downe thy fauourable looke (O ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent father) and giue care vnto our feruent Prayerse, haue compaſſion vpon vs, that crie out daily vnto thee, and lift vp our ſorrowfull eyes, and heauie mindes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy moſt excellent mercies ſeate, hauing this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured confidence, that thou art ready to forgiue, rich in
<pb facs="tcp:13277:31"/>louing kindnes towards ſuch as call vpon thee, and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding mightie in thy works, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Gods, wilt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe vs in ſo great diſtreſſe, and tribulation. Thou art moſt puiſſat, thou ſheweſt wonderfull things, &amp; thou art God alone. Teach vs therfore thy perfect waies, cauſe vs to walke in thy bleſſed truth: cal backe our wandring hart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, that it may ſtand greatly in feare of thy holy name. Thou verely haſt nobly
<pb facs="tcp:13277:32"/>made vs partakerse of thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent merey, but for aſmuch as we were very vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the hoſtes of the vngodly are riſen vp againſt vs, and the forefrone of curſed mens battailes haue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aulted vs, who neither regar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thee at all, nor make any account o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thy moſt bleſſed name &amp; pure doctrine, indeuoucing al only by their moſt lewd practiſes, thorow the ſame meane to deſtroy at one puſh both the true worſhinping of thee,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:32"/>and our Soules alſo.</p>
               <p>Seeing that therefore thou art a very mercifull God, long ſuffering, of great loue, and truth to truſt vnto, haue an eſpeciall regarde vnto the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy louing promiſe, be fauorable, ſtrengthen and defende them, aduaunce thy banner to our ſaluation, ſo that the cruel aduerſaries may be confouded, and that all may right well ſee and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently perceiue thee onely to be our moſt good and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:13277:33"/>God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the prosperous ſucceſſe of Christs kingdome against the enemies thereof.</head>
               <p>OVR daily petition is (O Almightie God) that the kingdome of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt may be aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, &amp; appeare at length to bee moſt perfect, which thing we now alſo deſire ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie inſtantlie in our heartie praters and humble ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. Be alwaies mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:13277:33"/>thereof (O good God) of his fat and moſt pleaſant ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which he made for vs vpon the altar of the Croſſe, and graunt, that by the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of his moſt perfect vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie and conqueſt, we may take both Saluation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull pleaſure. Although we deny not, but that the ſame ſhal come to paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our deſarts, who haue (through our manifold wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe) offended thee very many and infinite waies: yet
<pb facs="tcp:13277:34"/>for (thy tender louing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake) put them to ſhame and confuſion, that repoſe all their truſt in Charets, horſe, and worldly power: but raiſe and lift vp to ſaluation ſuch as are wholy bent to depend vppon thee, and bowe downe thy mercifull and fauourable eares, to heare the feruent prayers and petitions which we make vnto thy diuine maieſtie, for the mightie en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging of our Lord Ieſus Chriſts kingdome, through
<pb facs="tcp:13277:34"/>the ſame Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for comfort in perſecution.</head>
               <p>WEe perceiue moſt mercifull &amp; mighty God, that not onely Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, but alſo the power and ſtrength of the whole world conſpireth againſt thee and againſt thy Chriſt: which thinke thy Goſpell, and the redification of thy Church to be an intollerable bondage and hard yoke. Wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:13277:35"/>they labor by all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to breake aſunder the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties and congregations of the faithful, and caſt away all diſcipline. But for aſmuch as thou ſitteſt in heauen, and art not ignorant what the diuell and wicked fleſh goeth about, laugh thou to ſcorne their vaine counſels, &amp; bring their purpoſes to naught, let them feele thine anger to be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt them, and make them aſtonied at the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thine indignation, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13277:35"/>that they may not be able to deſtroy thy Church, ouer whom thou haſt appointed Ieſus Chriſt our onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, that in it he might raigne by the word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with inuinſible might and power. Wherfore grant vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, although vnworthie and ſhrinking children, ſuch faith and conſtancie, that we may find him, &amp; alſo confeſſe him, to be our onely King, and that we may nothing doubt but that wee bee his
<pb facs="tcp:13277:36"/>nation, people and heritage, being moſt aſſured of this, that he is of ſuch ſtrength and power, that with his word, more ſtrong then yron, he is able to deſtroy whom he wil, and breake them in peeces like earthen pots. Therefore (O God) turne the Kings and Princes of the world vnto thee, that they may be wiſe and vnderſtand, wherby they may vnfeinedly acknowledg, imbrace, and kiſſe the Sonne, leaſt when his anger ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:13277:36"/>once be kindled, they periſh and be deſtroied for euer. And when it ſhall bee thy good pleaſure, make them bleſſed for euermore, which commit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to thy gouernance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> protection. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for a true Subiect.</head>
               <p>AS it is thy godly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment (O Lorde God) that ſome ſhould beare rule in this world, to ſee thy glory ſet forth, &amp; the common peace kept: ſo it is thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againe, that ſome ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:13277:37"/>be ſubiects, and inferiours to other, in their vocation, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though before thée there is no reſpect of perſons. And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it is thy godlie will and pleaſure, to appoint and ſet me in the number of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects: I beſeech thee to giue me a faithfull &amp; boedient hart vnto the higher powers, that there may be found in me no diſobedience, no vnfaith ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no treaſons, no falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, no diſſimulation, no inſurrection, no commotion nor
<pb facs="tcp:13277:37"/>conſpiracie, nor any kinde of rebellion in word or deed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ciuil Magiſtrates, but al faithful obedience, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe, ſubiection, humilitie, and whatſoeuer elſe becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a ſubiect: that I liuing here in all lowlines of mind, may at the laſt day, through thy fauor, be lifted vp into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glory, where thou moſt mermcifull Father, with the Son and the holy Ghoſt, liueſt, and raigneſt very God for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:38"/>
               <head>For Fathers and Mothers.</head>
               <p>THe fruite of the wombe, and the multitude of children is thy gift and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, O Lord God, giuen to this end, that they may liue to thy glorie, and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of their neighbours. Foraſmuch therefore as thou of thy goodues haſt giuen me children: I beſeech thee giue me alſo grace to traiue them vp euen from their cradles in thy nurture, and doctrine, in thy holy lawes and bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:13277:38"/>ordinances, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry young age they may know thee, beleeue in thee, feare, loue, and obey thee, and dili\gently walke in thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements all the daies of their life, vnto the praiſe of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name: through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Of Children.</head>
               <p>THou haſt giuen a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement in thy lawe (O heauenly Father) that Children ſhould honor their Fatherse and Mothers: I
<pb facs="tcp:13277:39"/>moſt humblie beſeech thee therefore, to breath thy holie ſpirit into my breaſt, that I may reuerence and honor my Father and Mother, not only with outward ieſtures of my bodie, but alſo with the vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned affections of my heart, loue them, obey them, map for them, help them, and doe for them both in word &amp; déed, whatſoeuer lieth in my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, that thou ſeeing my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined hartygoodwil towards my parents, maiſt become
<pb facs="tcp:13277:39"/>my louing heauenly Father, and number me among thoſe thy children, whom from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting thou haſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be heires of thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kingdome: through thy welbeloued Sonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Of Houſeholders.</head>
               <p>TO haue children and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants is thy bleſſing, O Lord, but not to order them according to thy word, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth thy dreadfull curſe. Graunt therefore, that as
<pb facs="tcp:13277:40"/>thou haſt bleſſed me with an houſehold, ſo I may diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch, that nothing be commited of the ſame that might offend thy father lie goodneſſe, and be an occaſion of turning thy bleſſing into curſing, but that ſo many as thou haſt committed to my charge, may eſchue all vice, imbrace all vertue, liue in thy feare, call vpon thy holie name, learne thy bleſſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, heare thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word, and auoiding idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:40"/>diligentlie exerciſe themſelues, euerie one in his office, according to their vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and calling, vnto the glorie of thy moſt honorable name. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Of all Christians.</head>
               <p>ALbeit, O Heauenly FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all we that vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly profeſſe thy holy reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and faithfullie call on thy bleſſed name, are thy ſonnes and heires of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glorie, yet as all the members of a body haue not
<pb facs="tcp:13277:41"/>one office, ſo likewiſe we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing manx, and making one bodie, whereof thy dearely beloued Sonne is the head, haue not all one gift, neither are we all called to one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, but as it hath pleaſed thee to diſtribute, ſo receiue we: we therefore moſt hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly praythee, to ſend the Spirit of loue and concord among vs, that without any diſorder or debate, euery of vs may be conent with our calling, quietly liue in the ſame, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb facs="tcp:13277:41"/>to doe good vnto all men, by the true and diligent exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe therof, without too much ſéeking of our priuat gaine, and ſo order our ſelues in all poynts, according to thy godlie will, that by well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing wee may ſtoppe the mouthes of ſuch fooliſh and ignorant people, as reporte vs to be euill dooers, and cauſe them through our good workes, to glorifie thee our Lord God, in the ay of viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:42"/>
               <head>A Prayer meete for all men, and to beſaid at all times.</head>
               <p>O Moſt mercifull Father, grant me to couer with an ardent mind, thoſe things which may pleaſe thee, to ſearch them wiſely, to know them truly, and to fulfil them perfectly, to the laud and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of thy name, Order my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo, that I may doe that<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>which thou requireſt of me, and giue me grace, ſo that I may know it, and haue will and power to doe it, and that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:42"/>I may obtaine thoſe things which be moſt connenient to my ſoule. Cacious Lord make my way ſure &amp; ſtreight to thee, ſo that I fall not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween proſperitie and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirie, but that in proſperous things, I may giue thee thankes, and in aduerſitie be patient, ſo that I be not lift vp with the one, nor oppreſſed with the other. And that I may reioyce in nothing but that which moueth mee to thee, nor to be ſorie for any
<pb facs="tcp:13277:43"/>thing, but for thoſe things which draw me from thee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to pleaſe no bodie, nor fearing to diſpleaſe any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſids thee: moſt louing father, let all worldly things be vile vnto me for thee, and be thou my moſt ſpeciall comfort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al. Let me not be merie with the ioy that is without thee. And let me deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides thee: let all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour delight me which is for thee, and let all the reſt wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie we, which is not in thee.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:43"/>Make me to lift vp my hart oftentimes to thee: and when I fall, make me to thinke on thee, and be ſorie, with a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt purpoſe of amendement. Louing Lord, make me hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without faining, merrie without lightneſſe, ſad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out miſtruſt, ſober without dulnes, true without double<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, fearing thee without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, truſting in thee with out preſumption, telling my neighbors their faults meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without diſſimmulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb facs="tcp:13277:44"/>them with words and examples, without any moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, obedient without argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, patient without grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and pure without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: giue me alſo I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, a waking ſpirite, that no curious thought with draw me from thee. Let it be ſo ſtrong, that no filthie affection dram me backward, ſo ſtable, that no tribulation breake it: graunt me alſo to knowe thee, diligentlie to learne a godlie conuerſation
<pb facs="tcp:13277:44"/>to pleaſe thee: and finallie, hope to imbrace thee, for the precious blood ſake of that immaculate Lambe, our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with thee, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt, thrée perſons and one God, be all honor and glory, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the obtaining of ſaith.</head>
               <p>O Mercifull God, &amp; deare Father of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in
<pb facs="tcp:13277:45"/>whom as thou art well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſo haſt thou commanded vs to heare him, foraſmuch as he often biddeth vs to aſke of thee, and thereto promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that thou wilt heare vs, and graunt vs that, which in his name wee ſhall aſke of thee. Loe gracious Father, I am bold to beg of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, through thy Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, one ſparkle of true faith, and certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of thy goodneſſe and loue towards me in Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:45"/>where through, I being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the pardon of all my ſinnes, by the mercies of Chriſt thy Sonne, may be thankfull to thee, loue thee, and ſerue thee, in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, all the dayes of my life. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for repentance.</head>
               <p>MOſt gracious God, and mercifull father of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue ſinned and done wickedlie, and thorough
<pb facs="tcp:13277:46"/>thy goodneſſe haue receiued a deſire of repentance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this long ſuffering doth draw my hard hart: I beſeech thee for thy great mercies ſake in Chriſt, to worke the ſame repentance in me, and by thy Spirite, power and grace, to humble, mortifie and teare my conſcience for my ſinnes to ſaluation, that in thy good time, thou maiſt comfort and quicken me, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus Chriſt thy dearly beloued Sonne. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:46"/>
               <head>A Prayer for remiſſion of ſinnes, and for the comfort and true feeling of Gods ſauor and mercie.</head>
               <p>OH Lord God and deare Father, what ſhall I ſay that feele all things to be in maner with me, as in the wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked? Blindis my mind, croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is my will, and peruerſe concupiſcener is in me, as a ſpring or ſtincking puddie. Oh how faine is ſaith in me? How little is my loue to thée, or thy people? How great is ſelfe-loue? How hard is my
<pb facs="tcp:13277:47"/>heart, by the reaſon whereof I am moued to doubt of thy goodneſſe towards me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art my mercifufll father, and whether I be thy childe or no? Indeede wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thilie might I doubt, if that the hauing of theſe were the cauſe, and not the fruite ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thy Children. The cauſe, and not the fruite ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thy Children. The cauſe why thou art my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is the mercy, goodneſſe, grace and trueth in Chriſt Ieſus, the which cannot but remaine for euer. In reſpect
<pb facs="tcp:13277:47"/>whereof, thou haſt borne me this good wil, to bring me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Church by Baptiſme, and to accept me into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thy Children, that I might be holy, faithfull, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient and innocent, and to cal me diuers times by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring of thy word, into thy kingdome, beſides the innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable other benefits, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hether to powred vpon me; all which thou haſt done of this thy good will, that thou of thine owne mercie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:48"/>beareſt to me in Chriſt, and for Chriſt, before the world was made. The which thing as thou requireſt ſtreightly, that I ſhould beléeue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting, ſo wouldeſt thou that in all my deedes, I ſhould come vnto thee, as to a father, and make my mone without diſtruſt of being heard in thy good time, as moſt ſhall make to my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Loe therefore to thee déere father, I come through thy Sonue our Lord, Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb facs="tcp:13277:48"/>&amp; aduocate Ieſus Chriſt, who ſitteth on the right hand making interceſſion for me, and pray thee of thy great goodneſſe and mercy in Chriſt to be mercifull vnto me, that I may feele in deed thy ſweet mercie as thy Childe. The time. O deere father I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt not, but I pray thee, that I may with hope, ſtill expect and looke for thy help. I hope that, as for a little while thou haſt left me, thou wilt come and viſite me, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:49"/>that in thy great mercie, whereof I haue need, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my great miſery. Thou art wont for a little ſeaſon in thine anger to hide thy face from them whom thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt but ſurely, oh redermer in eternall mercies, thou wilt ſhew thy compaſſion. For when thou leaueſt vs, oh Lord thou doeſt not leane vs very long neither doeſt thou leaue vs to our owne loſſe, but to our Iuere and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: Euen that for holy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:49"/>ſpirit, with bigger portion of thy power and vertue, may lighten and theere vs, that the want of feeling to our ſorrow, may be recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed plentifully with the linely ſince of hauing thee to our eternal ioy: and therefore thou ſweareſt, that in thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer laſting mercie, thou wilt haue compaſſion on vs Or which thing to the ende we might be moſt aſſured, thine oth is to be marked, for thou ſaiſt, as I haue ſworne, that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:50"/>I will neuer bring any more the Waters to drowne the world. ſo haue I ſworne, that I will neuer more be angrie with thee, nor reprooue thee. The Mountaines ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue, and the Hils ſhall fall downe, but my louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall not mooue, and the band of my peace ſhallnot faile thee: Thou ſaieſt, thou the Lord our mercifull redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Déere Father, therfore I pray thée remember, euen for thine own truth and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb facs="tcp:13277:50"/>ſake, this promiſe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting couenant, which in thy god time, I pray thee to write in my hart, that I may know thee to be the only true God and Ieſus Chriſt whom thou haſt ſent, that I may loue thee with all my heart for euer: that I may loue thy people for thy ſake: that I may bee holy in thy ſight, through Chriſt, that I may alwaies, not only ſtriue againſt ſinne, but alſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſame, dailie more
<pb facs="tcp:13277:51"/>and more as thy children doe, aboue all things deſiring the ſanctification of thy name, the comming of thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the doing of thy will here on earth, as it is in heauen, &amp;c. through Ieſus Chriſt our redeemer, Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour and Aduocate. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for delinerance from ſinne, and to be restored to Gods grace and fauour againe.</head>
               <p>O Almightie and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Lord God, which haſt made heauen and earth,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:51"/>and all things therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: Ourcomprehenſible vnitie: O alwaies to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped moſt buiſſed Trmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: I humbly beſeeth thee and praye thee, by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and crucified hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of our I orde Irius Chriſt, that thou wouldeſt inclide and howe downe the great depth of thy deitie, to the bottomeleſſe priormy v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riticie. Driue from me all kinde of vice, wlikedueſſe and ſinne, and make in
<pb facs="tcp:13277:52"/>me a cleane heart, and renew in me a right ſpirice, for thy holy names ſake. O Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, I beſeech thy goodneſſe, for that exceeding great loue which drew thee out of thy Fathers boſome, into the wombe of the holy Virgine, and for the aſſumption of mans nature, wherein it hath pleaſed thee to ſaue me, and to deliuer me from eternall death, that thou wouldeſt draw me out of my ſelfe, into thee my Lorde God, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:52"/>grant this my loue mya reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer again to me thy grace, to increaſe and make perfect in me that which is wanting, to raiſe vp in me that which is fallen, to reſtore to me, that which I haue loſt, and to quicken in me, that which is dead and ſhould liue, that ſo I may become can ormable vnto thee in all my life and conuerſation, thou dwelling in mee, and I in thee, my heart being ſoupled with thy grae, and ſetled in thy faith
<pb facs="tcp:13277:53"/>for euer. O thou my God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſet at libertie my ſpirice from al inferiour things: go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne my ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo work, that both in ſoule and bodie, I may be haly and liue to thy glorite, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer neceſſart to be ſayd at all times.</head>
               <p>O Bountifull Lord Ieſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O ſweete Sauiour. O Chriſt the ſoune of God, haue vittie vpon me, mercifullie heare mee and deſpiſe not
<pb facs="tcp:13277:53"/>my prayerse. Thou haſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me of nothing, thou haſt redcemed me from the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of ſinne, death, and hell, neither with gold nor ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r, but with thy moſt pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oote once off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed vpon the Croſſe, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> owne blood ſhed once for all, for my ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: therefore caſt me not away, wham thou by thy great wiſdome haſt made: beſpiſe mee not, whome thou haſt redeemed with ſuch a precious treaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:54"/>nor let my wickedneſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy that which thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath builded: now whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt I liue, O Ieſus, haue mercie on me: for if I dye out of thy fauour, it will be too late afterward to call for thy mercie: whileſt I haue time to repent, looke vpon me with thy mercifull eyes, as thou diddeſt vouchſafe to looke vpon Peter thine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, that I may bewail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſinfull life, and obtaine thy fauour, and dye therein:
<pb facs="tcp:13277:54"/>I reknowledge that if thou ſhouldeſt deale with me ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to very iuſtice, I haue deſerued euerlaſting death. Therefore I appeale to thy high throne of mercie, truſting to obtaine Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, not for my merttes, but for thy merites, O Ieſu, who haſt giuen thy ſelfe an accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſacrifice to the Father, to appeaſe his wrath, and to bring all ſinners truly repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and amending their euil life, into his fauour againe.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:55"/>Accept me (O Lord) among the number of them that ſhall be ſaued, forgiue me my ſinnes, giue mee grace to leade a godlie and innocent life: graunt me thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdome, inſpire my hart with faith hope, and charitie, giue me grace to be humble in proſperitie, patient in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, obedient to my ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, faithfull vnto them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> truſt me, dealing truel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with all men: to liue chaſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e in wedlocke, to abhorre adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:55"/>formcation, and all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, to doe good after my poer to all men, to hurt no man, that thy name may be glorified in me, during this preſent life, and that I after ward may obtaine ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſting life: through the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and merites of thy paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the vvrote congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Christ.</head>
               <p>SHew thy ſelfe goutle and gracious (O Almightie God) towards thy beloued
<pb facs="tcp:13277:56"/>Church, for thy exceeding great glories ſake, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie moſt magnificent, that we may be miraculouſly deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the horrible fardle and cruell bondage of our deadly ſinnes: who haue he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been bondſlaues to the fleſh, and wretched priſoners of the Diuell, and yet thou vouchſafeſt to releaſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs the whole number of our deadly iniquities, and couered all haynous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Notwithſtanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:56"/>we are now alſo very vngratefull, and ſuch as be not worthie of thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous benefits, our earneſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is, that thou wouldeſt withould thy ſelfe from thy wrathful indignation. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thou art iuſtly angry with vs, but (for the glorie of thy name) repreſſe this furie which is ſtirred vp by reaſon of our grieuous ſinnes, and lead vs into the ſiraite way of perfice health for as much as it appertaineth not to thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:57"/>louing kindnes, to be alwaies offended with thy faithfull ſeruants, or to contiuue thy heauie wrath, and ſierce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, vnto many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Deale with vs after thy olde accuſtomed maner, &amp; not according to our leand deſerts, ſcatter abroade our cruell enemies, and put them to flight whome thou (being prouoked through our great default) wouldeſt that wée ſhould feele. Thou which in thy great wrath doſt kill and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:57"/>being pacified, quickened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: ſhew thy mercie and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health, like as thou haſt ſet deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before our eles, to the intrut thou wouldeſt both terrifie and chaſtice vs. Graunt that we (which haue heretofore been maruellous rebellions and very ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, may euer hereafter, giue obedient care to theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ngs which thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>akeſt, and willeſt vs to doe Let thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſpeakeable louing mercie and famous truth be linked
<pb facs="tcp:13277:58"/>in vs together, and vouchſafe that peace and righteouſneſſe may with an vndiſſoluble band ſticke faſt in our hearts, that when as thou haſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vs from the hands of the moſt outragious Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and his cruell champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we may yeeld vnto thee the plentifull fruites of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer vpo the xiij. Pſalme.</head>
               <p>O Lord, how long wilt thou forget me for euer?
<pb facs="tcp:13277:58"/>O good God how long wilt thou hide thy gracious coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from me? How long ſhall I be carried and toſſed about, with heauſe and trouble ſome cogitations and thoughts? How long ſhall my heart wither and drie vp with ſorrowe? But now O my Lord God, conſider me, regarde me with the eyes of thy mercie, he are mee O Lord, lighten mine eyes, and my vnderſtanding, O my God, leaſt I be blinded with
<pb facs="tcp:13277:59"/>the reprobate, and ſuperiſh in my ſins. I beſeech thee moſt humbly, let not my enemies glorie and triumph among themſelues, as though they had wonne the victorie: let them not riſe vp againſt me as if I were vanquiſhed grant me Lord, that my hart may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to thy ſaluation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo that with own voyce. I may ſing praiſes and render thankes to thee, for that through thy helpe, A aut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and brought againt
<pb facs="tcp:13277:59"/>into ioye after my gricuous tranſgreſſions and ſorrows. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer vpon the xiiij Pſalme.</head>
               <p>O Lord delier me from al impietie and vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſ: deliuer me from my blind ignorance, that I may earneſtly ſéeke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, for we be al generally borne in calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and forgetfulneſſe, and there is not one man, which can vnſhackle or deliuer him ſelfe by his owne propper ſtrength and vertue, there is
<pb facs="tcp:13277:60"/>no help but only by thy grace and power. O Lord, graunt that I may call vpon thee with an vnfained hart when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I ſhall be tempted by theſe aduerſaries. Let ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe of faith alwaies goe before me: let me not be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with feare of any thing, ſaue only of thy iudgements, let all my truſt, defence and fortreſſe be in thee, O Lord, Send, O good God, from thy celeſtiall Syon, that only protector, which ſhall deliuer
<pb facs="tcp:13277:60"/>thy people from the horrible captiuitie of a troubleſome conſcience, ſo that we may reidyce in him without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer vpon the xv. Pſalme.</head>
               <p>O Lord purge me againe, and iuſtifie me through faith from mine offences, that I may dwell in thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beruacle, and continue bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in thy holy Mountaine. Graunt me (O Lord) this benefit, that I may confeſſe thy truth without hypocriſie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:61"/>with an vpright hart. Grant me that I deceiue no perſon, neither by wrong to circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent any creature, Keepe me from flattering the peruerle and wicked men, that I may loue and obey thoſe which loue God in renerence, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer occaſion the wicked take thereby to ſlaunder me: let me not be trouble ſome or burdenous to any man, but that I may ſerue all with vnfained affection, to edifie my brethren thorow faith in
<pb facs="tcp:13277:61"/>Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A moditarion vpon the Lords Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OVr Father which art in heauen.</hi> We being glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly formed vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image of thy diuine maieſtie, &amp; crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thy gracious goodnes, to moſt high honor: how beit through ſin, diſſigured with vilenes, deſeruing damnatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and yet by Chriſts death re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed and reſtored vnto grace, to be Citizens with ſaints of the ſamilie of God,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:62"/>now altogether in Chriſtian vnitie, as members of one bodie, we pray, deſire, and truſt to obtaine of thee our heauenlie father, according vnto thy gracious goodneſſe mightie power and faithfull promiſe vnto vs that aſke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of thy grace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That thy name may be halowed.</hi> That thy diuine power and glorious maieſty may be certainly known, and reuerently honoured. That the hearts of vs men, by thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:62"/>word and praier may be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified from all ſin and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſo that we with all that we haue, ſeruing thee in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and righteouſneſſe, may ſo ſhine afore men vpon earth, that they may thereby be occaſioned to honour thee our Father, which art in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy kingdome come.</hi> That thy worde may be ſo fruitfullie preached amongſt vs thy people, that we may be throughly inſtructed, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:63"/>taught to bridel our ſenſuall appetites by natural reaſon, and to ſubmit our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s and reaſons vnto a godly ſpirite, and to trie our ſpirits by the true Scriptures. So that within vs may raigue the kingdome of God, which is neither meate nor drinke: which is neither ſuperſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ceremoutes, voluptuons pleaſures, nor vaiur glorie, but righteouſneſſe, peace and comfort in the holy Ghoſt, by the which we now taſting of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:63"/>thy heauenlie ioyes, may be made from henceforth wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of all worldlie vanities, continuallie looking &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the appearance and comming of thy eternall and euerlaſting kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thy will be done in earth as it is in Heauen.</hi> In Heauen the Angels of reuerent loue do thy will and commounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with comfortable cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ioyfull pleaſure. In hell the wicked Spirits thorowe malice and enuie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:64"/>repining and grudging, doe torment and vexe themſelues whatſoeuer they bee doing. And vpon earth, men being ſubiect vnto ſinne, doe thinke it is a labour and paine to be occupied in any thing that is good and godly. Wherefore we pray thee, that the grace of thy heauenly ſpirit may ſo worke in our earthly bodies, that wee being deliuered from ſinne and vanitie, may freelie delight and take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to doe thy will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb facs="tcp:13277:64"/>here on earth, as thy glorious Angels doe in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Giue vs this day our dailie bread.</hi> We hauing great néed and not able of our ſelues to deſerue any thing, beſeech thee of thy fatherly goodnes, to giue freely vnto vs all, ſo that none be hurt nor hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this day, when we crie vnto thee, conſtrained by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neede, not greedilie cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing (through vaine care a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt to morrow) our dailie
<pb facs="tcp:13277:65"/>Bread, our daily and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie foode and reliefe, both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ghoſtlie: and eſpei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie, ſo that the ſpirituall foode of Chriſts fleſh, and his blood, by dailie preaching of thy Goſpell, and the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, may repleniſh our heart, and mindes, with continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his death and paſſion, dailie to be vſed for our neceſſarie and ſpirituall conſolation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as
<pb facs="tcp:13277:65"/>we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</hi> We feeling and knowing our own ſinifulnes, doe deſire thy mercifull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of our faultes and treſpaſſes, which we haue committed againſt thee, ſo that we freely forgiuing al other that haue offended vs in any thing, whatſoeuer it be, may be ſure that mercie ſpringing in thee, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded vnto vs, &amp; being gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly offered of thee, hath bin thankfully receiued of vs,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:66"/>and being charitably vſed of vs towards other, ſhall moſt certainly bee confirmed and enlarged of thée towards vs: ſo that by free mercie ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; procéeding from thee, all faults may be freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen. Euen as thoſe which other haue committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, ſo likewiſe thoſe which we haue done againſt thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And leade vs not into temptation.</hi> Suffer not the Deuill, by the abuſe of thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:66"/>benefites, to leade vs Cap\tiues into deceitful and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable temptation, drawing vs by daintie meates vnto greedie Gluetonie, by money and rithes vnto vnſatiable couetouſnes, and by wealth and proſperity vnto pride and vaine-glorie, and by all thy godly and gracious gifts, vnto euery diueliſh and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But deliuer vs from euill.</hi> Deliuer our goods from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, our bodies from corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:67"/>our ſoules from dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Deliuer vs by Chriſt Ieſu from the bondage of ſinne, vnto the libertie of the Goſpell: ſo that from the danger of the diuell, and all his temptation, traming and inticing towards danmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we being deliuered, may ſerue thee in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of our life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thine is the kingdome, the power and glory, for euer and euer, Amen.</hi> For ſuch is
<pb facs="tcp:13277:67"/>thy riches and regiment, power and authoritie, praiſe and excellencie, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer treaſures, lands, and poſſeſſions, might, wiſdome, and ſuperioritie, dignitie, honour and maieſlie hath been, is, or ſhall be in any perſons, times and places, the ſame of equitie, dutie, and neceſſitie, begin, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and ende, ſo as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie, Veritie, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of thy onely kingdome, power and glorie may beſt
<pb facs="tcp:13277:68"/>appeare and be knowne, to be far paſt all creatures ability, vnderſtanding, or capacitie in thee onely Lorde God of truth, without beginning, change, or decay eternally: yea, euery other kingdome, power and glory, be but ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhadowes and ſhewes, ſeruing for this tranſitoric time, to make vs more mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and deſirous of thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall kingdome, power and glorie. By reaſon whereof out hope and the promiſe of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:68"/>eternall ſaluation, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in Chriſt be, Amen: that is to ſay, moſt certaine. So be it.</p>
               <p>ALmightie and euerli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, vouchſafe we beſeech thée to graunt vs perfect continuance in thy liuely faith, augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſame in vs daylie, till wée growe to the full meaſure of our perfection in Chriſt, whereof wée make our coufeſſion, ſaying.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Apostles_Creed">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:69"/>
               <head>The Crede of the Apostles.</head>
               <p>I Beleeue in God the father Almightie, maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth. And in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne our Lord. Who was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary. Suffered vnder Ponce Pilate, was crucified, dead and buried. He deſcended into hell. The third day he roſe again from death. He aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:69"/>From thence ſhall he come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beléeue in the holy Ghoſt. The holy eathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. The commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints. The forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes. The reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the bodie. And the life euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="confession">
               <head>The Confeſſion of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith.</head>
               <p>I Beleeue and confeſſe my Lord God eternall, infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, vnmeaſurable, incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, and inuincible,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:70"/>one in ſubſtance, three in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Father, Sonne, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, who by his almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power and wiſdome, hath not onely of nothing created heauen, earth, and all things therein contained, and man after his own Image, that he might in him be glorified, but alſo by his Fatherly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, gouerneth, maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, &amp; preſerueth the ſame, according to the purpoſe of his will: I beléeue alſo and confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt the only
<pb facs="tcp:13277:70"/>Sauiour and Meſſias, who being equall with God, made himſelfe of no reputation, but tooke on him the ſhape of a ſeruant, and became man in all things like vnto vs (ſinne except) to aſſure vs of mercy and forgiueneſſe. For when through our Father Adams tranſgreſſion we were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Children of perdition: there was no meanes to bring vs from that yoke of ſin, and damnation, but onely Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, who giuing
<pb facs="tcp:13277:71"/>vs that by grace, which was his by nature, made vs (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row faith) the Children of God, who when the fulneſſe of time was come, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the power of the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Mary (according to the fleſh) and preached on earth the Goſpell of ſaluation, till at length by tyrannie of the Prieſts, he was giltleſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned vnder Pontinus Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laie, then Preſident of Iurie, and moſt ſlaunderouſly han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:13277:71"/>on the Croſſe betwixt two theeues, as a notorious treſpaſſer, where taking vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the puniſhment of our ſinnes, he deliuered vs from the curſe of the lawe. And for as much as he being onely God, could not feele death, neither being only man could ouercome death, hee ioyned both together, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered his humanitie to be puniſhed with moſt cruell death: feeling in himſelfe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſeuere iudgement of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:72"/>God, euen as if he had been in the extreame torments of hell, and therefore cried with a loude voyce: My God, my God, why haſt thou for ſaken me: Thus of his free mercie without compulſion, he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp himſelfe as the onely ſacrifice, to purge the ſins of all the world, ſo that all other ſacrifices for ſin are blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and derogate from the ſufficiency hereof. The which death, albeit it did ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reconcile vs to God, yet
<pb facs="tcp:13277:72"/>the ſcriptures commonly do artribute our regeneration to his reſurrection: for as by riſing again from the graue the third day, he conquered death: euen ſo the victorie of our faith ſtandeth in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, and therefore without the one, we cannot feele the benefite of the other. For as by death ſinne was taken away, ſo our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe was reſtored by his reſurrection. And becauſe he would accompliſh al things,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:73"/>and take poſſeſſion for vs in his kingdome, he aſcended into heauen, to enlarge the ſame kingdome, by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant power of his ſpirit: by whom we are moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his continuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion towards God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vs. And although he be in heauen, as touching his corporall preſence, where the father hath now ſet him on his right hand, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto him the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of all things, as well
<pb facs="tcp:13277:73"/>in Heauen aboue, as in the Earth beneath, yet is he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs his members, euen to the end of the world, ini preſeruing and gouerning vs, with is effectuall power and grace, who (when all things are fulfilled, which God hath ſpoken by the mouth of all his Prophetes ſince the world began) will come in the ſame viſible forme, in the which he aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an vnſpeakable ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtie, power and companie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:74"/>to ſeparate the Lambes from the Goates, the Elect from the reprobate. So that none, whether he be aliue then, or dead before, ſhall eſcape his iudgement. Moreouer, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and confeſſe the holy Ghoſt, God equall with the Father and the Sonne, who regenerateth and ſanctifieth vs, ruleth and guideth vs in all truth, perſwading moſt aſſuredly in our conſciences, that we be the Children of God, Brethren to Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:13277:74"/>Chriſt, and tellowe heires with him in life euerlaſting. Yet notwithſtanding it is not ſufficient to beleeue, that God is omnipotent and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull: that Chriſt hath made ſatiſfaction; or that the holy Ghoſt hath his power and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: except we doe applie the ſame benefites to our ſelues, which are Gods Elect. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue therefore, and confeſſe one holy Church, which (as members of Ieſus Chriſt, the only head thereof) conſent
<pb facs="tcp:13277:75"/>in faith, hope, and charitie, vſing the giftes of God: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be temporall, orſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, to the profit and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Which church is not ſéene to mans eye, but only known to God, who of the loſt Sons of Adam hath ordained ſome as beſſels of wrath to dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: and hath choſen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as veſſels of his mercy to be ſaued: the which alſo in due time he calleth to inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie of life, and godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:75"/>to make them a glorious church to himſelfe. But that church which is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and ſéene to the eye, hath thrée tokens or marks wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may be diſcedice. Firſt, the word of God contained in the old and new Teſtament, which as it is aboue the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the ſame Church, and only ſufficient to inſtruct vs in all things concerning ſaluation, ſo it is left for all degrees of men to reade and vnderſtand. For without this
<pb facs="tcp:13277:76"/>word, neither Church, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel or decree can eſtabliſh any poynt touching Saluation. The ſecond, is the holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, to wit, of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per: which Sacraments Chriſt hath left vnto vs as holy ſignes and ſeales of Gods promiſes: for as by Baptiſme once receiued, is ſignified that we (as well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants as others of age and diſcretion) being ſtrangers from God by originall ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:76"/>are receiued into his familie and congregation, with full aſſurance, that although this roote of ſin lye hid in vs, yet to the elect it ſhall not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pured. So the Supper de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth, that God as a moſt prouident Father, doth not only feede our bodies, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſpiritually nouriſheth our Soules, with the graces and benefites of Ieſus Chriſt, (which the Scripture cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth eating of his fleſh, and drinking of his bloud) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13277:77"/>muſt we in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of theſe Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, followe mans phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, but as Chriſt himſelfe hath ordained, ſo muſt they be miniſtred: and by ſuch as by ordmarie vocation bee thereunto called. Therefore, wheſoeuer reſerueth or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippeth theſe Sacraments, or contrarywiſe contemneth them in time and place, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureth to himſelfe damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>The third marke of this
<pb facs="tcp:13277:77"/>Church, is Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline: which ſtandeth in admonition and correction of faults. The finiall end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is excommunication by the conſent of the Church, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, if the offender be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate. And beſides this Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall cenſure: I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge to belong to this Church, a politicall Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate: who miniſtreth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man Iuſtice, deſending the good, and puniſhing the euill, to whom we muſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:13277:78"/>honour and obedience in all things, which are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God. And as Moſes, Ezechias, Ioſias, and other godly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, purged the Church of God, from Superſtition and Idolatrie: ſo the defence of Chriſts Church appertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractes, againſt al Idolaters and Heretikes, wherein ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth only remiſſion of ſinnes purchaſed by Chriſts bloud, to al them that beleeue, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13277:78"/>they be Iewes or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and leades vs to vayne confidence in Creatures, and truſt in our own imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The puniſhment where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, although God oftentimes deferreth in this life: yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the general reſurrection, when our ſoules and bodies ſhall ariſe againe to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, they ſhall be damned to vnqueachable ſire, and then we, which haue forſaken all mans wiſdome, to cleaue vnto Chriſt, ſhall heare that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:79"/>ioyfull voyce. Come ye bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father, inherice ye the kingdome prepared for you, from the beginning of the world, and ſo ſhall goe triumphing with him in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and ſoule, to remaine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly in glory, where we ſhall ſee God face to face, and ſhall no more need one to inſtruct another, for we ſhall all know him, from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt: To whom with the Father, the Sonne and holy Ghoſt, be all praiſe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:79"/>honor, and glorie, now and for euer. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="Ten_Commandments">
               <head>The Commandements of God giuen by Moſes, and expounded by Chriſt.</head>
               <div n="1" type="tablet">
                  <head>The firſt Table.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THou ſhalt haue none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods bt me. Exo. 20. Deut. 6. I am the Lord thy God, which haue brought thee out of the land of AEgypt, out of the houſe of bondage.</hi> Chriſt. Mat. <hi>6.</hi> Heare Iſrael, Our Lord God is one Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:80"/>and thou ſhalt loue thy Lord God with all thy heart, and with all thy ſoule, and with all thy mind, and with all thy ſtrength.</p>
                  <p>Matth. <hi>4.</hi> Thou ſhalt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thy Lord God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ij. Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, nor in the water vnder the earth, thou ſhalt not bowe downe to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:80"/>them, nor worſhip them. For I the Lord thy God am a ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, and viſit the ſinnes of the Father vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhewe mercie vnto thouſands in t hem that loue me, and keepe my comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iohn. 1. No man hath ſéene God at any time. The only begotten Sonne, which is in the boſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hath declared him
<pb facs="tcp:13277:81"/>Chriſt. Iohn. <hi>4.</hi> God is a Spirit, and they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and truth. Acts <hi>18.</hi> For as much as we are the generation of God, wee ought not to thinke, that the Godhead is like vnto Gold, Siluer or Stone, grauen by craft, or imagination of man. <hi>1.</hi> Iob. <hi>5.</hi> Babes, kéepe you from Images.</p>
                  <p>Sap. <hi>14.</hi> Curſed is the I dol that is made with hands: yea, both it, and he that made
<pb facs="tcp:13277:81"/>it, becauſe it was called God, whereas it is but a fraile thing. For the vngodly and his vngodlines are both like abhominable vnto God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>iij. Thon ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine. For the Lord will not hold him guiltles, that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Mattth. <hi>5.</hi> Ye haue heard how it was ſayd vnto them of olde tyme: Thou ſhalt not forſweare thy ſelfe, but ſhalt perfourme thyne
<pb facs="tcp:13277:82"/>othes to the Lord. But I ſay vnto you, Sweare not at all, neither by heauen, for it is Gods ſeate, nor yet by the earth, for it is his footeſtoole, neither by Ieruſalem, for it is the ciite of the great King: neither ſhalt thou ſweare by thy head, becauſe thou cauſt not make one white hayre. or a blacke. But let your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication be yea, yea, and nay, nay: for whatſoeuer is more then that, commeth of euill. Eccl. <hi>24.</hi> The man that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:82"/>vſeth much ſwearing, ſhall be filled with iniquitie, and the plague ſhall not be out of his houſe. Zachar. <hi>5.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, that the curſe of God ſhall reſt in the houſe of fhim that ſweareth falſty, and conſume it with the Timber and ſtones thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>iiij. Remember that thou keepe holy the Sabbath day, ſixe dayes ſhalt thou labour and doe all that thou haſt to doe, but the ſeuenth day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:83"/>in it thou ſhalt doe no maner of worke, thou, thy ſonne, and thy daughter, thy man ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and thy mayd ſeruant, thy cattell, and the ſtraunger that is within thy gates, for in ſixe daies the Lord made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, the Sea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeuenth day: wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeuenth day and hallowed it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Matth. <hi>12.</hi> It is lawfull to doe a good déede on the Sabboth day. Matth. <hi>2.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:13277:83"/>For the ſonne of man is Lord euen of the Sabboth day.</p>
                  <p>The Lord ſaith by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay, Eſay <hi>26.58.</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes <hi>4.</hi> That his Sabboth is hallowed and kept: when we reſt and ceaſe to doe our owne wayes: when we in word, thought and déede ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his wil, and not ours: and when we ſuffer him to do his workes in vs. That at the laſt wee may come to that Sabboth and true reſt, euen eternall life, which Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:13277:84"/>the Lord of the Sabbath hath obtained for vs by his blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="tablet">
                  <head>The ſecond Table.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>v. Honour thy Father and thy Mother, that thy daies may be long in the land which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Matth. <hi>15.</hi> Honor thy Father and Mother: that is the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that hath any promiſe, that thou maieſt be in good eſtate and liue long on the Earth. By this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement
<pb facs="tcp:13277:84"/>Chriſt teacheth vs not only to haue our Father and Mother in reuerence, and to obey them, as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was ſo ſubiect vnto his mother, he Virgine Mary. But alſo to miniſter vnto their neceſſities. Match. <hi>15.</hi> Marke <hi>7.</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>3.</hi> He that feareth the Lord, honoureth his Father and Mother, and doth them ſeruice, as it were vnto the Lord himſelfe, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor thy Father in deede and word, and in all patience, that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:85"/>thou mayſt haue Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and his bleſſing ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde with thee at the laſt. The bleſſing of the Father buyldeth vp the houſes of the children: But the mothers curſe, rooteth the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>vj. Thou ſhalt doe no mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Chriſt. Math. <hi>5.</hi> Ye haue heard how it was ſaid vnto them of the old time. Thou ſhalt not kill. Whoſoeuer killeth, ſhall be in daunger of iudgement. But I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:85"/>you: whoſoeuer is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie with his Brother, ſhall be in dauger of iudgement: Whoſoeuer ſayth to his brother, Racha, ſhall bee in daunger of a Counſell. But whoſoeuer ſayth, thou foole, ſhall bee daunger of hell fire. Item, yee haue heard how it is ſayd, thou ſhalt loue thy neighbours and hate thyne enemies: But I ſay vnto you, loue yor enemies, bleſſe them that curſe you, doe good
<pb facs="tcp:13277:86"/>to them that hate you, pray for them that doe you wrong, and perſecute you: that ye may be the children of your Father which is in Heauen. For he maketh the Sonne ariſe on the euill, and on the good, and ſendeth his rame on the iuſt and on the vniuſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>vij. Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Matth. <hi>5.</hi> Ye haue heard how it was ſaid to them of the olde time: Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie. But I
<pb facs="tcp:13277:86"/>ſay vnto you: that whoſoeuer looketh on a wife, luſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her hath committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultlerie with her alreadie in his heart. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>6.</hi> knowe yee not that your bodies are the members of Chriſt: Shall I now take the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, and make them the members of an Harlot? God forbid. Doe you not know that he which coupleth himſelfe with an Harlot, is become one body? For they (ſaith he) ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:13277:87"/>two in one fleſh. But he that is ioyned vnto the Lord is one ſpirit. Flee fornication: Euery ſinne that a man doth is without the bodie, but he that is a fornicatour, ſinneth againſt his owne bodie. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowe ye not, how that your bodies are the tempſes of the holy Ghoſt, which dwelleth in you, whom you haue of God, and how that you are not your owne? For ye are dearely bought, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore glorifie God in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb facs="tcp:13277:87"/>and in your Spirites, which are Gods. Hebr. <hi>13.</hi> Let wedlocke be had in price in all poynts, and let the Chamber be vndefileld: for whoremongers and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers God will iudge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>viij. Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Matth. <hi>10.</hi> Steale not. Detraude no man. Matth. <hi>5.</hi> If any man wil ſue thee at the law, and take thy coate from thee, let him haue thy cloake alſo. Giue to him that aſketh, and from
<pb facs="tcp:13277:88"/>him that would borrow, turne not away. <hi>1.</hi> Corin. <hi>6.</hi> Now is there vtterly a faulte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, becauſe ye goe to lawe one with another. Why rather ſuffer ye not wrong? Why rather ſuffer yee not your ſelues to be robbed? Nay, yee your ſelues doe wrong and robbe, and that the brethren. Epheſ. <hi>4.</hi> Let him that did ſteale, ſteale no more, but let him rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with his hands ſame good thing, that he may haue
<pb facs="tcp:13277:88"/>to giue him that needeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>jx. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Mark. <hi>10.</hi> Beare no falſe witneſſe. Matth. <hi>13.</hi> I ſay vnto you, that of euery idle worde which men ſhall haue ſpoken, they ſhall giue accounts at the day of Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Epheſ. <hi>4.</hi> Wherefore put away lying, and ſpeake euery man the truth to his neighbour: for as much as we are members one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:89"/>Let no filthie commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication proceede out of your mouthes: but that which is good, to edifie with all when neede is, that it may haue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with the hearerse. Let al bitterneſſe, fierceneſſe, and wrath, roaring and curſed ſpeaking, be put away from you. Ephe. <hi>5.</hi> Let not frithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, fooliſh talking, nor ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting (which are not comely) be once named among you: but rather giuing of thanks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>x. Thou ſhalt nor deſire thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:89"/>neighbours houſe: thou ſhalt not deſire thy neighbours wife, nor his mayde, nor his Oxe, nor his Aſſe, nor any thing that is thy neighbours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt, Math. <hi>7.</hi> Whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ye would men ſhould do to you, euen ſo do ye to them. Marke. <hi>7.</hi> To loue a mans neighbour as himſelfe, is a greater thing then all burnt Offerings and Sacrifices.</p>
                  <p>Matth. <hi>14.</hi> Be not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with iuſt, for the care of this world, and the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:90"/>of riches choke the word, Hebrewes. <hi>13.</hi> Let your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation be without coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and bee content with that ye haue alreadie. <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>6.</hi> Godlineſſe is great riches, ſo a man be content with that he hath. For we brought nothing into the world, and it is a plaine caſe, that we carrie nothing out. When we haue food and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let vs therewith be content. They that will be rich, fall into temptations
<pb facs="tcp:13277:90"/>and ſuares, and into many fooliſh and noyſeme luſtes, which drowne men in perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and deſtrucion. For Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſniſſe is the roote of all euil, which while ſome luſted after, they erred form the faith, and tangled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with many ſorrowes. Deut. <hi>6.</hi> Theſe words which I commaunde thee this day ſhall be in thyne heart, and thou ſhalt whet them in thy Children, and ſhalt talke of them, when thou art at home
<pb facs="tcp:13277:91"/>in thine houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou lieſt downe, and when thou riſeſt vp, and thou ſhalt binde them for a ſigne vpon thine head. And they ſhall be papers of remembraunce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thine eyes, and thou ſhalt write them vpon the poſſes of thy houſe and vpon thy gaies. Deut. <hi>3.</hi> Take heede and heare all theſe words which I commaund thee, that it may go wel with thee, and with thy Children
<pb facs="tcp:13277:91"/>after thee for euer, when thou doeſt that which is good and right in the ſight of the Lord thy God. Deut. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>See thou do that which is right, and in the ſight of the Lord, that thou mayſt proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Deut. <hi>12.</hi> He ſhal not de after al theſe things that we do here this day, euery man what ſee moth him good in his owne eyes, but whatſoeuer I commaund you, take hée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e do, and put nought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nor take ought thereiro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:92"/>Deuter. <hi>27.</hi> Curied bee he that maintaynech not all the words of the law to do them. Galat. <hi>3.</hi> Chriſt hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs from the curſe of the law, in as much as he was made accurſed for vs (for it is written: Curſed is euery one that hangeth on trée) that the bleſſings of Abraham might come on the Gentiles, through Ieſus Chriſt, that we might receiue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Spirit through faith. Ierem. <hi>31.</hi> This is the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:92"/>Teſtament that that I wil make with the houſe of Iſrael. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe dayes (ſay the Lord) I will put my Lawes in their minds, and in their hearts I wil write them, and their ſinnes and iniquities I wil no more remember. And I will be with my people.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſvveete and louing promiſes of almightie God in ſuch as keepe his Commaundements.</head>
               <head type="sub">Deut. xxviij.</head>
               <p>IF thou hearken diligently vnto the voyce of the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:13277:93"/>thy God to obſerue and doe all his Commaundements: Bleſſed ſhalt thou be in the towne, and bleſſed in the fields. Bleſſed ſhall be the fruite of thy bodie, the fruite of the ground, and the fruite of thy Cattell, the fruite of thyne Oxen, and the flockes of ſheepe. Bleſſed ſhall thy Barnes be and thy ſiore, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhalt thou be both when thou goeſt out, and bleſſed when thou commeſt in.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="oration">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:93"/>
               <head>The Oration of Iob in his moſt grieuous aduerſitie and loſſe of goodes.</head>
               <p>Iob. 1.</p>
               <p>NAked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I turne againe, and the Lord hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as it hath pleaſed the Lord, ſo is it done, now bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the name of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer in proſperitie.</head>
               <p>I Giue thee thankes O God Aloughtie, which not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty haſt indued me with the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:94"/>giftes of nature, as reaſon, power, and ſtrength, but alſo haſt plentifully giuen me the ſubſtance of this world. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (O Lord) that theſe are thy gifts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe with holy Saint Iames that there is no perfect nor good gift, but it commeth from thee (O Father of light) which giueſt freely &amp; caſteſt no man in the teeth, I acknowledge with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Agge, that gold is thine and Siluer is thine, and to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:94"/>whome it pleaſeth thee thou giueſt it, to the godly, that they may be the diſpoſers and diſtributers thereof, and to the vngodly, to heape vp their damnation with all. Wherefore my moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God. I humbly beſeech and deſire thee, to frame in me with the holy Spirit, a faithfull heart and readie hand, to diſtribuce theſe thy good gifts accoding to thy will and pleaſure, that I treaſure not vp heere where
<pb facs="tcp:13277:95"/>theeues may rob, and moths corrupt: but to treaſure vp thy heauenly kingdome, where neither Theefe may ſteale, nor moth defile, to myne owne comfort (whom of thy mercie thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to reward therfore) to the good example of the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and meeke of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and to the glorie of thy name. To whome with thy Sonne, and holy Ghoſt be al honor and praiſe, world without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:95"/>
               <head>A godly prayer to be ſayd in thy aduerſitie and trouble.</head>
               <p>O Lord GOD, without whoſe will and pleaſure a Sparrowe doth not fall on the ground, ſaeing it is thy will and permiſſion that I ſhould be in this miſerie and aduerſitie, and ſéeing alſo thou doeſt puniſh mee with aduerſitie and trouble not to deſtroye mée, and caſt me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: but to call me to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and ſaue mee: for whom thou doeſt loue, him
<pb facs="tcp:13277:96"/>doeſt thou chaſten. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, ſeeing afflictions and aduerſitie worketh patience, and who ſo patiently beareth tribulation, is made like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Sauiour Chriſt the head: Finally, ſeeing that in all tribulation and aduerſity, I am in aſſurance of comfort at thy gracious hands, for thou commaundeſt me to call vpo thee in time of tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and haſt promiſed to heare and ſuccour me: grant me therefore, O almightie
<pb facs="tcp:13277:96"/>God and mercifull Father, in all trouble and aduerſitie to be quiet, without impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and mururing, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcouraging and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to praiſe and magnifie thee, to put my whole truſt and confidence in thee, for thou neuer forſakeſt them that truſt in thee, but workeſt all for the beſt to them that loue thee, and ſeeke the glorie of thy name. Tot hee he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for euer: So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:97"/>
               <head>A prayer to be ſayd before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Communion.</head>
               <p>O Father of mercie and God of all conſolation, ſeeing all creatures doe knowledge and confeſſe thee to be their gouernour and Lord, it becommeth vs the workemanſhip of thine owne handes, at all times to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and magnifie thy godly Maieſti.e Firſt, for that thou haſt created vs to thine owne Image and ſimilitude, but chiefly, becauſe thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered
<pb facs="tcp:13277:97"/>vs from that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death and damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, into the which Sathan drewe mankinde by the meanes of ſinne: from the bondage whereof neither man nor Angell was able to make vs free: but thou (O Lord) rich in mercie, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in goodneſſe haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided our redemption, to ſtand in thine onely and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued ſonne, whom of very loue, thou diddeſt giue to be made man, like vnto vs in all
<pb facs="tcp:13277:98"/>things, ſine xcepted, that in his bodie, he might receiue the puniſhment of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by his death, to make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction to thy iuſtice, and by his reſurrection to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him that was the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of death, ſo to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine life to the world, from which the whole ſpring of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam was moſt iuſtly exiled.</p>
               <p>O Lord, we acknowledge that no creature was ble to comprehend the length and the breadth, the deepeneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:98"/>and heigot of that moſt exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent loue, which moued thee to ſhew mercie, where none was deſerued, to promiſe and giue life, where death had gotten the victorie, to receiue vs into thy grace when we could do nothing, but rebel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy maieſtie, O Lord, the blind dulneſſe of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, will nto ſuffer vs ſufficiently to weigh theſe thy moſt ample benefites: yet neuertheleſſe, at the commaundement of Ieſus
<pb facs="tcp:13277:99"/>Chriſt our Lord, we preſent our ſelues to this thy Table (which hee hath left to bee vſed in remembrance of his death, vntill his comming againe) to declare and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before the world, that by him alone we haue receiued libertie and life: that by him alone thou doeſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge vs to be thy children and heires: that by him alone wee haue entraunce to the trone of thy grace: that by him alone, we are poſſeſſed
<pb facs="tcp:13277:99"/>in our Spiritual kingdome, to eate and drinke at his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, with whom we haue our conuerſation preſent in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and by whom our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſhall be raiſed vp againe from the duſt, and ſhall be placed with him in that end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ioy, which thou (O fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercie) haſt prepared for thine elect before the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the world was laid. And theſe moſt ineſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefits, we acknowledge and confeſſe to haue receiued
<pb facs="tcp:13277:100"/>of thy free mercie and grace, by chine onely beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt. For the which therefore we thy congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, moued by the holy Spirice: render to thee all thankes, praiſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for euer and euer. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ A thankes giuing after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</head>
               <p>MOſt mercifull father, we render to thee all praiſe, thankes, honour, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:100"/>glorie, for that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee of thy great mercy to graunt vs miſerable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo excellent a gift and treaſure, as to receiue vs into the fellowſhip and companie of thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, whom thou haſt deliuered to death for vs, and haſt giuen him vnto vs, as a neceſſarie foode and nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto euerlaſting life. And now we beſéech thée alſo (O heauenly father) to graunt vs this requeſt, that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:101"/>thou neuer ſuffer vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo vnkind, as to forget ſo worthie benefites, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imprint and faſten them ſure in our hearts, that we may grow and inicreaſe dayly more and more in true faith which continually is exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in all manner of good workes: and ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (O Lord) confirme vs in theſe perillous dayes and rages of Sathan: that we may conſtantly ſtand and continue in the confeſſion of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:101"/>the ſame, to the aduaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thy glorie, which art God ouer all things bleſſed for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A comfortable Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Lord God almigbtie, and Father moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, there is none like thee in heauen or in earth, which workeſt all things, for the glorie of thy name, and the comfort of thine elect. Thou diddeſt once make man ruler ouer all thy creatures, and placed him in the garden of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:102"/>all pleaſure, but how ſoone (alas) did he in his felicitie, forget thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Thy people Iſrael alſo in their wealth, did euermore run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, abuſing thy maniſld mercies: like as all fleſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timually rageth, when it hath gotten libertie, and externall proſperitie. But ſuch is thy wiſedome adioyned to thy mercies (deare Father) that thou ſeekeſt all meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to bring thy children to the ſure ſence, and liuely fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb facs="tcp:13277:102"/>of thy fatherly fauour. And therefore, when proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie will not ſerue, then ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou aduerſitie, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly correcting all thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom thou receiueſt into thy houſhold. Wherfore I wretched and miſerable ſinner, render vnto thee moſt humble and heartie thankes, that it hath pleaſed thee to call me home to thy folde, by thy fatherly correction at this preſent, whereas in preſperlite and aduerſitie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:103"/>I did neglect thy greace offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto me. For the which negligence and many other grieuous ſinnes, where of I now accuſe my ſelfe before thee, thou mighteſt moſt iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue giuen me vp into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate minde, and indurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hart, as thou haſt done others. But ſuch is thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (O Lorod) that thou ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt5 to forget al my offences, and haſt called me of thy good pleaſure from all idolatrie, to profeſſe thy name, and to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:103"/>ſuffer ſome Croſſe amongſt thy people for thy truth, and Goſpel ſake, and ſo to be thy witneſſe with the Prophets and Apoſties, yea with thy dearely beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our head, to whom thou doeſt, being heere, faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me like: that in his glorie, I may alſo be like him when he ſhall appeare. O Lord God what am I vpon whom thou ſhouldeſt ſhewe this great mercie? O moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Lord forgiue me my
<pb facs="tcp:13277:104"/>vnthankefulneſſe, and all my ſinnes, for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake. O heauenly Father, increaſe thy holy Spirit in me, to teach my heart to crye Abba, deare Father, aſſure me of thy eternall election in Chriſt, to reueale thy will more and more towards me, to confirme mee ſo in thy trueth, that I may liue and dye therein, and that by the power of the ſame Spirite, I may boldlie giue an account of my faith
<pb facs="tcp:13277:104"/>to all men, with humbleneſſe and meekeneſſe, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of thy moſt holy name. Thorowe Ieſus Chriſt our Lor and onely Sauiour. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A meditation for a vvoman vvith childe, and ſpecially vvhen ſhe entreth in to trauell.</head>
               <p>O Almightie and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, which of thy bountifull goodneſſe haſt fructified my wombe, and of thy gracious bleſſing hath created mee a reaſonable
<pb facs="tcp:13277:105"/>creature, I moſt heartily thanke thee, not only for this thy gracious gift, but alſo for that thou haſt at all times, ſince I conceiued, preſerued me from all perils, both of ſoule and bodie, and haſt ſo moderated all my nips, pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, throwes, and pangs, that I haue hetherto right well eſcaped them, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge (O Lord) iuſtly for our ſinfull tranſgreſſion of thy commaundements, thou ſaidſt vnto the firſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:105"/>and in her to vs all: I will increaſe thy ſorrowe when thou art with childe: with paine ſhalt thou bring forth thy children. And our paines therefore that we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in this behalfe, are none other thing but a worthie Croſſe layde vpon vs, by thy godly ordinance, to the which with heart and minde, I humbly ſubmit me, truſting ſurely, and being fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in my faith, that thou calleſt none into perrill and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:106"/>daunger, but both thou canit and wilt at conuenient ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon deliuer them. Thou (moſt gracious GOD) haſt commaunded vs in all our trouble to call vpon thee for ayde and helpe: and not only haſt commaunded vs, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of thy mercifull goodneſſe haſt promiſed to vs good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, ſaying: Call vpon mee in the time of trouble, and I will deliuer thee. O good Lord, how greatly doe theſe words comfort my hart,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:106"/>and ſuſtaine my ſillie ſoule? Who would not greatly reioyce, that knoweth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely almighty God to be preſent with him in his trouble? Saith not God thus: Or euer they cal (ſaith he) I ſhall aunſwere them, while they are yet but thinking how to ſpeake, I ſhal beare them, and in the Pſalme, I am with him, ſaith God, in his trouble, out of which I will deliuer them. What a comfortable
<pb facs="tcp:13277:107"/>Lord is this? He is more readie to help, then we to call for help. He is more readie to giue grace, then we to aſke it. There was neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yet, that with a ſure faith aſked grace of this Lord, but he had it.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſaith, aſke and ye ſhall haue. Euery one the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centeth none. Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you (ſaith Chriſt) whatſoeuer you ſhal aſke my Father in my name, he ſhall giue it you. Our Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:13277:107"/>Chriſt ſaith this, and he is God. And ſhall not I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my Lord God his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and promiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s? Verely, I will ſticke ſurely to it. For ſure I am, that ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall heauen and earth periſh, then Gods promiſ. be vnperſourmep. For albeit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man naturally is a lyar and deceiver, yet God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies true and iuſt in all his words and promiſes. I will therefore make my ſuite vnto him, whom I neede not goe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:108"/>farre to ſeeke, for he is eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where preſent iwth his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, and is nigh vnto al them that call vpon him faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And thus I will pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer of a vvoman vvith Child.</head>
               <p>FAther of mercy, and God of comfort and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I thy poore handmaid, humbly beſeech thee, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, and in his bleſſed and holy name that thou wilt vouchſafe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:108"/>to torgiue me all my ſinnes and treſpaſſes, that I haue heretofore offended thy holy Maieſtie, either in thought, conſent, delectation, word or deede and that thou wilt hereafter during my life, mercifully preſerue me from tranſgreſſing of thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, and dayly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in me perfect repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for my ſinnes, a ſure purpoſe of amendment of life, a diligent ſtudie to walke in thy commaundementes,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:109"/>increaſe in me alſo a liuely faith, a ſure hope, and and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent charitie. Ingreffe in me humbleneſſe of heart, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, cleanneſſe of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Graunt me, that I may be wiſe, ſad, ſober, diſcreete, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect, and well aduiſed in all my ſayings. And that I may ſtrongly ouercome all the temptations of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the Deuill, the world, and the fleſh. And that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſleeping, waking, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:109"/>drinking, or whatſoeuer I doetall may be to thine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie.</p>
               <p>Graunt me alſo that I may humbly reuerence, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully loue mine Huſband, and be obedient to all his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, lawfull, and godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts. And chiefly of all, graunt me (O Lord) that I may feare and dread thee. For well aſſured I am, that look how high the heauen is, in compariſon of the Earth, and ſo great is Gods mercie
<pb facs="tcp:13277:110"/>towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare him. Looke how wide the Eaſt is from the Weſt, ſo farre hath he ſet our ſinnes from vs, Yea, like as a Father piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne children, euen ſo is the Lord mercifull to them that feare him. And as touching my deliuerance of this burthen and thy graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gift, I am right well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that vnleſſe thou proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per my trauell, all womens help, &amp; all phificke is in vaine: but my full truſt is, that like
<pb facs="tcp:13277:110"/>as thou haſt created this child in me, and haſt breathed into it the ſpirit of life, ſo at ſuch time, as ſhall be ſeene moſt meete to thy godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, thou both cauſt, and wilt proſper the childs birth and my deliuerance. In con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof, I humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beſeech thee of thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly pittie, ſo ſtreng then me in this my daungerous labour and trauell: and ſo ſuſtaine mee, that I may patientlie beare all the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:111"/>throwes and pangs, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy promiſe, ſuffer me not to be tempted aboue my ſtrength, but in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of my temptation, make a way to come out, that I may beare it. Increaſe my faith, O moſt mercifull Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt, that I may conſtantly beleeue thy word, which ſaieſt, ye ſhall be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, but your ſorrowe ſhall be turned into ioy. A woman when ſhe trauaileth hath ſorrowe, for her hower
<pb facs="tcp:13277:111"/>is not come, but when ſhe is deliuered of the childe, ſhe thinketh no more of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh for ioy that a man childe is borne into the world. I beſeech thee the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in the daungerous time of my crauell, graunt me ſpeedie deliuerance, and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full beholding of my childe, that I being a merrie mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may render vnto thee honor, laude, praiſe and thankes, for thine aboundant mercie, and gracious giftes
<pb facs="tcp:13277:112"/>and benefites. And finally, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, I beſeech thy gracious goodnes, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due my child with grace, that it may be one of the number of thine elect, Babtized, and regenerated in the holy Ghoſt. And that at the yéeres of diſcretion, it may learne to know thee, and knowing thee, may truſt ſurely in thy mercy, and truſting in thy mercie, may heartile loue thee, louing thee, may feare to diſpleaſe thee, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:13277:112"/>to diſpleaſe thee, may walke and continue in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And finally attaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uerlaſting ioy and felicitie. Through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which liueth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>igneth with thee, and the holy Ghoſt, world without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe is deliuered.</head>
               <p>O My Lord GOD, I thanke thee with all my heart, wit, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:113"/>and power, for that thou haſt vouchſafed to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me out of the perill of this moſt dangerous trauel, and haſt ſent into this world, out of my wofull wombe this childe a creature of thine owne faſhioning, forming, and ſhape, like vnto the reſt of the Children of thy creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for which I am not able worthely enough of my owne faile nature, to giue to thee condigne thankes, praiſe, honour, and glorie, for thy ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13277:113"/>great benefites ſhewed vnto me, in pulling me out from the pittes brincke of death, eaſing and releeuing all my wofull ſorrowes, laborious panges, and moſt grieuous throwes, bitter anguiſhes, and vnſpeakeable paynes, which I could neuer haue aſcaped, without thy moſt ſingular ayde, helpe, reliefe, and ſuccour: wherefore, I thy moſt humble hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide, with ſtedfaſt and pure heart and handes, doe powre
<pb facs="tcp:13277:114"/>our before thee my Lorde God and onely Sauiour, theſe my ſimple prayers of thankes-giuing (the fruite of my faith, hope, truſt, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and aſſured confidence) which I haue in thee as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining my ſelfe, that now thou haſt preſerued me for a further tryall of my nocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſeruice towards thee, in this vaile of tranu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corie life, wherein I may haue time, by thy diuine permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſufferance, to direct
<pb facs="tcp:13277:114"/>all my ſteppes in thy wayes, and to honour and glorifie thee in my ſoule, and bodie, with condigne thankes in reioycing in thy holy name, according to thy moſt bleſſed word, wherein thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that a woman as long as ſhee is in trauell of her childe bearing, ſhee is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull, heauie, and full of anguiſh, and intollerable pames, but as ſoone as the chile is borne, ſhe learneth ſtraighe wayes to forget all
<pb facs="tcp:13277:115"/>her paynes, not remembring them any longer, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to reioyce, for that ſhe hath brought foorth a childe into the world. Euen ſo O Lord fareth in with me, thy poore, humble, and obedient ſeruant, now reioyſing, in that it hath pleaſed thee, to make me a glad mother, in bringing foorth this childe, whom now I doe preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of thy diuine maieſtie, with an earneſt zeale of a godly ſpirit, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:115"/>moſt pure affection, praying and beſeeching thee euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, here to preſerue this child, according to thy moſt holy will, that it may enioy the benefites, of all thy heauenly Sacraments, to liue, and ſerue thee in pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, as a faithfull member of the Chriſtian congregation, wherein thy name by it may be glorified, honoured, and prayſed world without end. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:116"/>
               <head>A prayer vvhen a man commet home from his labour.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing, O Lord, more like to thy holy nature, then a quiet minde. Thou haſt called vs out of the troubleſome, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe of the world, into that thy quiet reſt and peace which the world cannot giue, being ſuch a peace, that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all mens vnderſtanding. Houſes be ordained for vs, that thereby we might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended from the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urie of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:116"/>weather, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oyles of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>O gracious father, graunt that through thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy my bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ier into this houſe, from outward actions, but ſo that it may become luxome, and obedient to the ſoule, and make no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance againſt the ſame, that in ſoule and bodie, I may haue a godly quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and peace, to praiſe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:117"/>thy holy name. So be it.</p>
               <p>Peace bee in this houſe, and to all that dwell in the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thinke what a returne, and how merrie a returne it will be, to come to our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, moſt quiet, and moſt happie home. Then will all griefe and ſorrowe ceaſe. Whatſoeuer here is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and ioyfull, the ſame is nothing but a very ſhadowe in compariſon of that which is to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:117"/>
               <head>A prayer for the ſicke.</head>
               <p>O LORD looke downe from heauen, behold, viſite, and relieue this thy ſeruant: looke vpon him with the eyes of thy mercie, giue him comfort and ſure confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in thee, defend him from the daunger of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and keepe him in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall peace and ſafetie: through Ieſus our Lord. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:118"/>
               <head>¶ Another prayer for the ſicke</head>
               <p>HEare vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ghty and moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ifull GOD and Sauiour, entend thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed goodneſſe to this thy Seruant, which is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with ſickneſſe, viſite him (O Lord) as thou diddeſt Peters wiues mother, and the Captaines ſeruant. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vnto this ficke perſon his former health (if it be thy will) or els giue him grace to take thy viſitation, that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:118"/>after this payuefull life en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, he may dwell with thee in life euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another prater for the ſicke.</head>
               <p>O Lord Ieſu Chriſt thou only Sonne of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and omni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fficient Sauiour, we moſt humbly beſeech thee, deliuer this ſicke and weake perſon, now being in great paines, and at the poyne to depart out of this world, from all vgliſome
<pb facs="tcp:13277:119"/>and terrible aſſaults and temptations of the Deuill, ſinne, and Hel. Deliuer him (O Lord) as thou deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redſt Noe from the raging waues of the Sea. Lot from the diſtruction of Sodome. Abraham from the feare of the Chaldees. The Children of Iſraell, from the tyrannie of Pharao, Dauid from the hand of Goliah, the three men from the violence of the fierie Fornace in Babilon. Daniell from the mouth of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:119"/>the Lyons, Ionas from the bellie of the Whalefiſh, and Peter from the priſon of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode. Euen ſo, O gracious Lord, deliuer the ſoule of this perſon, both now and whenſoeuer he ſhall departe hence, from all perrilland daunger. Open vnto him at the hower of death, the doore of Paradiſe, the gates of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the entrie of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life. O Lord Ieſus Chriſt, forgiue him all his ſinnes, and leade him with
<pb facs="tcp:13277:120"/>ioy, into the kingdome of thy heauenly father, euen vnto the boſome of Abraham, and appoynt him vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting reſt, that he may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iayce with thee, and with all the elect Children of God, in euerlaſting life. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The ſticke mans Prayer.</head>
               <p>LOrd hearken vnto my prayer, and giue eare to my moſt humble requeſtes. O moſt mercifull God: O father of all mercies, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13277:120"/>of our Lord and ſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me a ſruner. Haue pietie on me, and quickly helpe me noore wretch, for the moſt better paſſion, and moſt precious death of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt thy onely beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Sonne, and our alone redeemer, and Sauiour. Enter not into iudgement with thy ſetuant, O Lord, Haudle me not according to my deſerts and merites, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there reward me afeer mine
<pb facs="tcp:13277:121"/>iniquities, but for thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nite and vnmeaſurable boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and exceeding great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, receiue me, and take me into thy fauour. I miſerable and weake creature, am in thy hand, I am thy boud ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant and thy debter, O moſt gentle God, O moſt fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Father, forſake me not, caſt mee not away, poore wretch that I am. For I am thine with all there euer I can make. No man is able to ſtrengthen mee, no man is
<pb facs="tcp:13277:121"/>able to deliuer me, no man is able to helpe me, but thou alone. Thou art the true helper in aduerſitie. Thou art the moſt ſure and preſent comforter of all neceſſitie. Thou alone art our helper, our Bulwarke, our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſe, and our moſt mightie and ſtrongly defended tower. Thou, O God, art our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuge, thou art our helper in all our tribulations. In thee O Lord, doe I truſt, let me not be confounded. Let
<pb facs="tcp:13277:122"/>me neuer be put to ſhame, let me not be deceiued of my hope, but preſerue me, for thy righteouſneſſe ſake. Bowe downe thine eare vnto me, make haſte to deliuer me. Be my befender, O God, and my ſtrong hold, thou ſhat mayeſt ſaue me. For thou art my ſtrength, and my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, yea, thou art my God, and my de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ies are in thy hands.</p>
               <p>Lighten thy countenance vpon thy ſeruant, and ſaue
<pb facs="tcp:13277:122"/>me for thy mercies ſake, O Lord. And foraſmuch (O ſooecte father) as it is thy godlie y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, to call me now from this miſerable life and wretched morld, I moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntirely beſeech thee to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me, in this agonie of death, that neither Sathan nor his Miniſters preuaile againſt me, but that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e faithfull and conſtant vnto the ende, in the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thy holy name, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for full remiſſion of all
<pb facs="tcp:13277:123"/>my ſinnes, in the precious blood of thy weldeloued Sonne and my onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chrſt, and that I departing in this faith, and perfect truſt, may bee placed among thy bleſſed saints and heauenly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, and ſo for euer and euer remaine with thee in glorie. Graunt this, O moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Father, for thy deare Sonnes ſake, Ieſus Chriſt our alone mediatour and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="will">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:123"/>
               <head>My Testament.</head>
               <p>THis I make my Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and laſt Will, in the name of the eternall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, in whoſe name I was baptized. In whom onely I hope and beleeue to be ſaued. Amen.</p>
               <p>Firſt I bequeath my ſoule into thy hands, O God, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt firſt made me, and thou haſt giuen thy Sonne to become man, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:124"/>dyed for my ſinnes, and for the ſinnes of the people. O father for thy ſonnes ſake haue mereie vpon me.</p>
               <p>O Lord Ieſu Chriſt, thou Sonne of God, thou haſt bought me with thy precious blood by one oblation, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently for all that beleeue in thee. O Chriſt, God and man, which are in Heauen, haue mercie vpon me, and be thou my mercifull mediator for me vnto thy Father, that I may be ſaued.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:124"/>O holy Ghoſt, God conqual with the father &amp; the ſonne, haue mercie vpon me, worke thy diume power in me tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thy gracious mipirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Drame me vnto Ieſus Chriſt, that I may finde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and be ſaued. Amen.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part.</p>
               <p>As concerning my bodie: that I bequeathe vnto the earth, from whence it came.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="confession">
               <head>My Conſiſſion.</head>
               <p>I Knowledge and confeſe with all my heart, that I
<pb facs="tcp:13277:125"/>am a ſinner, yea, ſuch a ſinner as hath neede of the grace, mercie, and fauour of God. <hi>My faith ioyned with hope.</hi> I beleeue that the Lord will haue mercie vpon me, for he hath firſt made me, and if it ſhall pleaſe him, he may ſaue me: This I beleeue, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I liue or dye, I am the Lords.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>My hope.</head>
               <p>I Hope that I ſhall find both grace and mercie for my ſinnes of God the Father, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb facs="tcp:13277:125"/>for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake, in him I beleeue, he is my re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deemer, he liueth for euer and euer: He maketh inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for ſinnes.</p>
               <p>So this I know, that now I am a corruptible body, but I hope through Chriſt to riſe an vncorruptible body. Now a mortall bodie, but through Chriſt and his merites, I hope to haue, though now an earthly bodie, then an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly bodie. For as many as ſhall be ſaued, ſhall ſhine
<pb facs="tcp:13277:126"/>in the kingdome of God, as bright as the Sunne. This my faith and hope I lay vp in my minde, the mind of my Soule, truſting onely to be ſaued, thorowe the merites of Ieſus Chriſt, God and man, which is in Heauen. From whence we looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the which ſhall change our vile bodie, and make it like his owne moſt glorious bodie, whereby he is ablel to ſubdue all things vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. O Chriſt haue mercie
<pb facs="tcp:13277:126"/>vpon mee, thou haſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med mee, O Chriſt ſaue me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Sicke.</head>
               <p>OH how ſicke am I? My weakeneſſe increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth more and more. Lord be mercifull vnto me, and giue mee grace pacientlie and thankefullie to beare the croſſe, and in the middeſt of this my ſickeneſſe, alwaies to ſay: Thy will O heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father bee done, and not mine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:127"/>
               <head>Another Prayer for the Sicke.</head>
               <p>O Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which art the onely health of all men liuing, and the euerlaſting life of them which dye in thy faith: I wretched ſinner, giue &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mic my ſelfe wholy to thy moſt bleſſed will. And I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſure, that the thing cannot periſh which is committed vnto thy mercie, moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee (O Lord) to giue me grace, that I may
<pb facs="tcp:13277:127"/>now willinglie leaue this fraile &amp; wicked fleſh, in hope of the reſurrection, which in better wiſe ſhall reſtore it to me againe: I beſeech thee (O moſt mercifull Ieſu Chriſt) that thou wilt by thy grace make ſtrong my ſoule, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all temptations, and that thou wilt couer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend my with the Buckler of thy mercie, againſt all the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the Diuell. I ſee and acknowledge, that there is in my ſelfe, no helpe of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:128"/>life and faſuation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my conſidence, hope, and truſt, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in thy moſt mercifull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I haue no merites <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good workes which I may alleage before thée. Of ſinnes and euill works, (alas) I ſee a grace heape, but through thy mercie I truſt to be of the number of them to whom thou wilt not impute their ſinnes, but take and accept me for righteous and iuſt, and to be the inheritour of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glorie. Thou (O
<pb facs="tcp:13277:128"/>moſt mercifull Lord) waſte borne for my ſake. Thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſuffer both hunger and thirſt for my ſake. Thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt preach, and teach, thou diddeſt pray and faſt for my ſake. Thou dideſt all good woorkes and deedes for my ſake. Thou ſufferedſt moſt greeuous paynes and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for my ſake. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, thou gaueſt thy moſt precious body to dye, and thy moſt bleſſed blood to be ſhed on the Croſſe for my ſake.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:129"/>Now moſt mercifull Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, let all theſe things profite me, which thou freely haſt giuen me, which haſt giuen thy ſelfe for me: let thy blood cleanſe and waſh away the ſpottes and foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of my ſinnes. Let thy righteouſnes hide and couer my vnrighteouſneſſe. Let the merites of thy paſſion, and blood, be the ſatiſfaction for my ſinnes. Giue me Lord thy grace, that my faith, and perſwaſion in thy blood wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:13277:129"/>not in me, but euer be firme and conſtant, that the hope of thy mercie, and life euerlaſting neuer decay in me, that Charitie waxe not colde in me: finally, that the weakeneſſe of my fleſh, be not ouercome with the feare of death. Graunt me alſo (O moſt mercifull Sauiour) that when death hath ſhut vp the eyes of my bodie: yet the eyes of my Soule may ſtill behold and looke vnon thee, and that when death hath
<pb facs="tcp:13277:130"/>taken away the vſe of my tongue and ſpeech yet that my heart may crye, and ſay vnto thee, O Lord, into thy hands I giue and commit my ſoule. Lord Ieſu take my Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A thankes giuing to God for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the faithfull out of this vvorld.</head>
               <p>O How can we (moſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father) render vnto thee ſufficient thankes for thine ineſtimable good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe toward thy faithfull
<pb facs="tcp:13277:130"/>ſeruants? Whom thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of this wetched world, vouchſafe to place in thy heauenly Ringdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the glorious companie of thy holy Angels, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saints. O full precious is the death of the faithfull, in thy ſight. Bleſſed are the dead that dye in the Lord. For they are at reſt from their painfull trauels and labour. The ſoules of the righteous, are in thy hand, O God, and the paine of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:131"/>death ſhall not touch them. In the ſight of the vnwiſe they appeare to dye, but they are in peace. They ſhine as the ſparkes, that runne through the red buſh. They gliſter as the ſhyning hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. They are as the ſtarres, world without end. They are as the Angels of God, They are clad with white garments, and haue golden Crownes vpon their heads. Tey doe ſeruice day and night before the glorious
<pb facs="tcp:13277:131"/>Throne of thy Diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie. They neither hunger, nor thirſt any more, neither doth the Sunne, or any heate fall vpon them, for the Lambe, which is in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of the Throne, gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them, and leadeth them vnto the liuing fountaine of waters. They followe the Lambe, whitherſoeuer he goeth. They haue ſuch ioyes, as eye hath not ſeene, nor eare hath heard, neither is there any heart able to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:132"/>thinke them, infinite and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable are thy treaſures (O Lord) which thou haſt layde vp for them, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part in thy faith. For theſe thy fatherly benefites to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſoule of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and for that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee, to call this our Chriſtian brother, from this vale of miſerie, vnto thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome we giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee moſt heartie thankes, humbly beſeeching thee, that thou wilt take like care for
<pb facs="tcp:13277:132"/>vs, and ſo gouerne vs, with thy holy Spirit both in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in health, that we may liue a good and godly life in this preſent world, and whenſoeuer it ſhall be thy good pleaſure to call vs hence, we may with ſtrong faith in thee, and in thy ſonne Chriſt Ieſu our Lord, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend both our bodies, and ſoules into thy mercifull hands, and through thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be placed in thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous kingdome, among thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:133" rendition="simple:additions"/>faithfull choſen people, and ſo for euer and euer, praiſe and magnifie thee our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, to whom with thy dearly beloued Sonne, Ieſu Chriſt our Lord, and Sauiour, and the holy Ghoſt that moſt ſweete com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter, bee all glorie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, world without end. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:133"/>
               <head>A Prayer of the comming of Chriſt to iudgement, and of the reward both of the faithfull and vnfaithfull.</head>
               <p>OH Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Sonne of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing God, by whom all things were made, are ruled and gouerned, as of thy loue for our redemption, thou diddeſt nto diſdaine to be our mediacour, and to take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee our nature, in the wombe of a Virgin purely, and without ſinne, by the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:134"/>operation of the holy ſpirit, that both thou mighteſt in thine owne perſon, woonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beautifie, and exalt our nature and worke the ſame in vs alſo: firſt aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the giltineſſe of ſinne, by remiſſion, then ſinne it ſelfe by death, and laſt of all, death, by rayſing vp againe theſe our bodies, that they may be like vnto thine owne glorious, and immortall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, according to the power, wherewith thou art able to
<pb facs="tcp:13277:134"/>ſubiect all things vnto thee: as (I ſay) of the loue for our redemption, thou becameſt man and that moſt poore, and afflicted vpon earth, by the ſpace of three and thirtie yeeres at the leaſt, in moſt humilitie, and paydeſt the brice of our ranſome, by thy moſt bitter death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for the which I moſt hartely giue thankes to thee: ſo of the ſame by loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs in thy good time, thou wilt come againe in the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:135"/>cloudes of Heauen, with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and great glorie, with flaming fire, with thouſands of Saints, with Angelles of thy power, with a mightie crie, ſhoure of an Archangel, and blaſt of a Trumpe, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly as a lightning, which ſhmeth from the Eaſt, &amp;c. when men thinke leaſt, euen as a Theefe in the night, when men be aſleepe, thou wilt ſo come, I ſay, thus ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly in the twinekling of an eye, all men that euer haue
<pb facs="tcp:13277:135"/>been, be, and ſhall be, with women and Children ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing before thy tribunall iudgement ſeate, to render account of all things, which they haue thought, ſpoken, and done againſt thy lawe, openly, and before all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, Saints, and Deuils, and ſo to receiue the iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of thy vengeance if that they haue not repented, and obeyed thy Goſpell, and ſo depart from thee to the Deuill and his Angels, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:136"/>all the wicked, which euer haue been or ſhall be, into Hell fire, which is vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and of paynes intolle ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, eaſelleſſe, endleſſe, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, euen from the face of thy glorious and mightie power: but if they haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented and beleeued thy Goſpell: If they be found watching with their Lamps and Dyle in their hands: if they be found readie appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled, with the wedding garment of innocencie; if
<pb facs="tcp:13277:136"/>they haue not hardned their harts, and hoorded vp the Treaſure of thy vengrance, in the day of wrath, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, but haue vſed the time of grace, the acceptable time, the time of ſaluation, that is, the time of this life, in the which thou ſtretcheſt out thy hand, and ſpreadeſt thine armes, calling and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto vs, to come vnto thee, which art meeke in hart, and lowly, for thou wilt eaſe all that labour and are
<pb facs="tcp:13277:137"/>heauie ioden. If they hane viſited the ſicke, and priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, comforted the comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, fed the hungrie, clothed the naked, lodged the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourleſſe. if they haue not laden their hearts with Gluttonie and ſurfetting, and carefulneſſe of this life. If they haue not digged and hid their Talent in the ground doing no good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, but haue been faithfull to occupie thy giftes to thy glorie, and here waſhed their
<pb facs="tcp:13277:137"/>garments in thy blood by heartie repentance, then ſhall the Angels gather them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, not as the wicked, which ſhall be collected as Faggoctes, and caſt into thy fire, but as the good wheate that is gathered into thy Barne: then ſhall they be caught vp to meete thee in the Cloudes: then ſhal their corruptible bodie, put on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruption: then ſhall they be indued with immortalitte and glorie: then ſhall they be
<pb facs="tcp:13277:138"/>with thee, and goe whither thou goeſt. Then ſhall they heare: Come ye bleſſed of my Father, poſſeſſe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you from the beginning.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall they be ſet on Seates of Maieſtie, iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the whole world, then ſhall they reigne with thee for euer, then ſhall God be all in al with them, and to them, then ſhall they enter and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite heauenly Ieruſalem, and the glorious reſtfull
<pb facs="tcp:13277:138"/>land of Canaan, where it is alwayes day and neuer night, where is no maner of weeping, teares, infirmitie, hunger, colde, ſickeneſſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, malice nor ſinne: but all wayes ioye without ſorrow, mirth without meaſure, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure without paine, heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harmonie, moſt pleaſant melodie, ſaying and ſinging: Holy, holy, holy, Lord God of hoſts, &amp;c. Finally, the eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not heard, neither hath it
<pb facs="tcp:13277:139"/>entred into the heart of man, that they ſhall then inherite and moſt ſurely inio, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though here they be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, priſoned, burned, ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Sathan, tempted of the fleſh, and intangled with the world, where through they are inforced to crye: Thy kingdome come Lord Ieſus, &amp;c. How amiable are thy Tabernacles.</p>
               <p>Like as the Hart deſireth the water brookes, &amp;c. Now, let thy Seruants departe in
<pb facs="tcp:13277:139"/>peace: I deſire to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and to be with Chriſt: we mourne to our ſelues, wating for the deliuerance of our bodies, &amp;c. O graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord, when ſhall I finde ſuch mercie with thee, that I may repent, beleeue, hope, and looke for theſe things, with the fruition of thoſe he auenly ioyes, which thou haſt prepared for all them that feare thee, and to reſt with thee for euer more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:140"/>
               <head>A prayer concerning life euerlaſting, the place vvhere it is, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable ioyes thereof.</head>
               <p>THat there is an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life none will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but ſuch as will denie God. For if he be true and iuſt (which he muſt needes be, or els he is not God) then can there not be but an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. That he hath both ſpoken it, and promiſed it in Matth. <hi>25.1.</hi> Cor. <hi>16.</hi> Hebr. <hi>4.11.</hi> and <hi>13.1.</hi> Peter. <hi>1.</hi> it plainly appeareth, and els
<pb facs="tcp:13277:140"/>where in very many places. So that to deny an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, is to deny God, to deny Chriſt, and all that euer he did: alſo to denie all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and religion, to condemne of fooliſhneſſe all good men, Martyrs, Confeſſours, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, Prophets, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes. Finally, the denyal of eternal life, is nothing els but a denyall of the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie of the Soule, and ſo a playne making of man no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better then beaſts. If
<pb facs="tcp:13277:141"/>it ſo be, let vs then cate and drinke, for to morrowe we ſhall dye. Lord preſerue vs from the ſaduciall and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiall impietie, and graunt vs for thy mercies ſake (deare God) that we may be aſſuredly perſwaded, that there is in deede an eternall life, and bliſſe with thee, for them that put their truſt in thee: amongſt whom, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count me for thy mercies ſake.</p>
               <p>Againe, this eternall life
<pb facs="tcp:13277:141"/>and the place appoynted for them that be thy ſeruants, all men doe graunt to be with thee, becauſe thou art euery where: therefore eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life is euery where.</p>
               <p>For they by thy word doe knowe, that in almuch as no man can ſee thee and liue, this eternall life and thy bleſſed preſence is moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, and had in fruition after in an other world, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by corporall death, they dodepart, and are tranſlated
<pb facs="tcp:13277:142"/>to a place aboue them, where thou dwelleſt in a light, whereunto no man can ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach. Abrahams boſome (they reade) was aboue, as the place of the wicked was alowe and beneath. Helias was caught vp into Heauen, and thy Sonne our deare Sauiour prayed, that where he is, thoſe alſo might be, which thou haddeſt giuen him, and might ſee his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Now here (deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tehr) we learne by thy ppirit
<pb facs="tcp:13277:142"/>was aſcended and taken vp in his very bodie into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whether Stephen loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp and ſaw thy Chriſt ſtanding on thy right hand: to whom he prayed. Oh Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.</p>
               <p>Graunt, I beſeech thee gracious God and Father, that I may haue a cleane heart, more and more to ſee thee, and ſo in ſpirit to ſee and looke often vpon this place, whither bring me at
<pb facs="tcp:13277:143"/>the length in bodie alſo I humbly pray thee.</p>
               <p>Now, what a thing this euerlaſting life is, no man is able to conceiue, much leſſe able to vtter. For the peace of God which is eternall life, paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. The eye hath not ſeene, the eare hath not heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can mans heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thoſe things, which thou (deare God) haſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for them that loue thee. Whatſoeuer therefore can
<pb facs="tcp:13277:143"/>be ſpoken or imagined of the kingdome, of the clearneſſe, ioy and felicitie of the ſame, is nothing in compariſon, as we may ſee by the Prophets, which becauſe they could not otherwiſe, vnder corporall things haue ſhadowed the ſame: ſo that the confidence of eternall life what a thing it is, can in no wiſe be tolde. Howbeit ſomewhat we may be brought into ſome ſight of it, by earthly things, to thinke on this ſort.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:144"/>If God hath giuen heere ſo many things, in a ſtrange place, how many are the great good things that be at home? If in a priſon are ſo many mercies how many are they in the Palace? If the wicked haue ſo many bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites, what is the ſiore, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thy ſeruants, Oh Lord? If thy Children finde ſuch comforts in the day of teares and mourning, what ſhall they finde in the day of the Marriage? If which
<pb facs="tcp:13277:144"/>beaſtes men being, haue the vſe of innumerable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, Oh how many are the bleſſings which they ſhall enioy with thy Angels and with thee thy ſelfe (O deare God) when they ſhall ſee thee, and haue the fruition of thee, in whom is fulneſſe without lothing of all good and faire things, ſo that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more deſired, and that for euermore? This thy children doe not ſee, as they now beleeue it: I ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:145"/>that euen in their bodies, they ſhall ſee it for euer, as Iob ſaid. They beleeue that they ſhall ſee thee, and their owne eyes behold thee, when theſe our corporall eyes, our bodies being rayſed ſhall doe their duties. Such a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thee, they beleeue to haue, as ſhall not be onely intellectuall, and by faith, as now it is: but euen a full ſight, and fruition, yea a coniunction, and fellowſhip with thee. Now they ſee but
<pb facs="tcp:13277:145"/>in a glaſſe, euen in a darke ſpeaking: but then they ſhall ſee face to face. For faith, though it be the ſubſtance of things hoped for, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine darke ſight of thee: yet it may not be compared to the reward of faith and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſight, which we ſhall ſee in the life to come, when faith and hope ſhall ceaſe. Now thy children knowe that they be thy Sonnes, though it yet appeare not what they ſhal be. We know
<pb facs="tcp:13277:146"/>(ſay they) that when our Chriſt, God, and man ſhall appeare, then ſhall we be like vnto him, for we ſhall ſee him, euen as he is.</p>
               <p>Oh great prerogatiue, to ſee Chriſt is he is. Which is not to be conſidered ſo much for the manhood, as for the godhead it ſelfe: as Paule doth alſo write, that when all things are ſubiect vnto the ſonne, then ſhall he be ſubiect vnto thee (deare Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo) ſo that God may
<pb facs="tcp:13277:146"/>be all in all. And therefore Chriſt our Sauiour prayed for vs, that we might knowe thee, the only true God: not that our Chriſt thy Sonne is not with thee, the true co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall and ſubſtantiall God, but that we might knowe how that after the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch a myſterie of his mediatorſhip, ſhall not be in heauen, as it is now in earth. Then thou bleſſed Trinitie, God the Father, God the Sonne, and God the holy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:147"/>Ghoſt, ſhall be all in all: thou ſhalt be the ende of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires: thou ſhalt be looked vpon with out ende, thou ſhalt be loued without loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, thou ſhalt be praiſed without wearineſſe. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though lothſomnes be wont to followe fulneſſe, yet our fulneſſe in the contemplation of thy pleaſures, ſhall bring with it, now kynd at all of loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomneſſe. Societie of ioyes ſhall be in the beholding of thee. Pleaſures are on thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:147"/>right hand for euer. We ſhal be ſatiſfted, when we ariſe after thine Image, I meane in the reſurrection. Oh deare father, ſhow thy ſelfe vnto vs, and we aſke no more. Oh graunt vs with thy Saints in euerlaſting life to praiſe with perpetuall praiſes, thy holy name. Happie then, and happie againe were we, if that day were come, that we might ſing with thy Angels, Elders, and innumerable thouſands, a newe ſong, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:148"/>ſay, thou Chriſt Ieſus, which waſt ſtaine, art worthie to receiue power and riches, and wiſedome, and ſtrength, and honour, and glorie, and bleſſing. In this bleſſed life all kind of maladies, griefes, ſorrowes and euils, be ſarre away, and all full of all kind of myrth, ioy and pleaſure. Oh that we might ſee now, a little with Saiut Iohn, that holy Citie, nowe Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, deſcending from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan, prepared of God as a
<pb facs="tcp:13277:148"/>Bride trimmed for her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. Oh that we might now ſomething heare the great voyce ſpeaking out of the throne, behold the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them, and they ſhall be his people, and he ſhall be vnto them their God, he wil wipe away all teares from their eyes, and death ſhall be no more, nor weeping, nor cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor ſorrowe, for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer things are gone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:149"/>
               <head>A prayer of death, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie it bringeth.</head>
               <p>WHat other thing do wee daylie in this preſent life, then heape ſinne vpon ſinne, and hoorde vp treſpaſſe vpon treſpaſſe. So that this day is worſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes then yeſterday, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of dayes ſo ſinnes, and therefore thy indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, good Lord, againſt vs, but when we ſhall be let goe out of the priſon of this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and ſo taken into thy
<pb facs="tcp:13277:149"/>bleſſed companie, then ſhall we be in moſt ſafetie of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie, and ſaluation, then ſhall come vnto vs, no ſickeneſſe, no neede, no payne, no kinde of euill to ſoule or bodie, but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer good we can wiſh, that ſhall we haue, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we loath, ſhall be farre from vs. O deare Father, that we had faith to behold theſe things accordingly. Oh that our hearts were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded thereof, and our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb facs="tcp:13277:150"/>inflamed with the deſire of them. Then ſhould we liue in longing for that which now we muſt lothe. O helpe vs, and graunt that we being ignorant of things to come, and of the time of our death, which to thee is certaine, may ſo liue, and finiſh our iourney here, that we may be readie, and then depart when our departing may make moſt to thy glorie and our comfort, through Chriſt. What is this life,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:150"/>but a ſmoke, a vapor, a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, a warfare, a bubble of water, a word, graſſe, a flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer? That thou ſhalt dye it is moſt certaine, but the time, no man can tell when. The longer in this life thou doeſt remaine, the more thou ſinneſt, which will turne to thy more paine. By cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death, our mynds be often (in a manner) oppreſſed with darkeneſſe, becauſe we doe but remember the light of the bodie, forgetting the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:151"/>light of the minde, and for thy reſurrection. Hereto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the good things, that after this life ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, without wauering in certeintie of faith, and ſo ſhall the paſſage of death be more deſired. It is like a ſayling ouer the Sea, to thy home and countrie. It is like a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, or purgation to the health of ſoule and bodie: it is the beſt Phiſition: it is like to a womans trauaile. For as the childe being deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:151"/>commeth into a more large place then the wombe, wherein it did lye before, ſo myſoule being deliuered out of the bodie, commeth into a much more larger and fayrer place, euen into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A deuout prayer to be ſaid daylie.</head>
               <p>O Almightie and eternal God, which vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeſt that we as it were hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueuly Children, ſhould euery one of vs call thee our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly
<pb facs="tcp:13277:152"/>Father. Graunt that among vs be pureneſſe and example of innocent life, thy moſt holy name may be ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, that all other Nations beholding our goodneſſe and vertuous deedes, that thou workeſt in vs, may be ſtirred to hallowe and glorifie thee. Graunt (O Lord) that the kingdome of thy grace and mercie, may reigne continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in our hearts, ſo that we may be worthie to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Realme of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:152"/>glorie and maieſtie. Graunt that vnto the very death, we refuſe not to followe thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine will, and that we, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the example of the celeſtiall Citizens, agreeing together quietly vnited in ſpirite, all controuerſie in opinions layd apart, the luſtes of the fleſh being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and the flattering aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes of the world and the Deuill ouercome, neuer wraſtle againſt thy moſt holy will, but obey it in al things.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:153"/>Graunt (O Lord) for our bodie needefull ſuſtenaunce, that we may the more freely ſerue thee. Giue vs (we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee O mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) that Hearuenly bread, the bodie of thy Sonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the very foode and health of our ſoules: giue vs the bread of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine precepts, that we may truely walke, and liue after them.</p>
               <p>Giue vs the bread of thy heauenly word, which is the
<pb facs="tcp:13277:153"/>ſtrong fortreſſe and ſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Soules, that we being well fed and ſilled with this foode, may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily runne to the celeſtiall feaſt, where as is no hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Graunt (O Lord) that we paciently beare and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our enemies, and ſuch as hurt vs, and willingly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue the offences committed againſt vs, that ſo we may finde the Lord in forgiuing vs our treſpaſſes, milde and mercifull. Graunt (O Lord)
<pb facs="tcp:13277:154"/>that we be not vtterly led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptation, that there by we ſhould be loſt. But in all perilles of temptation and in the middeſt of the ſtormie tempeſts and tribulations, let vs thy children, perceiue and feele thy fatherly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, readie to helpe vs, leaſt that we be (ouercome with the naughtie craftes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites of the tempter) ſhould be drawne into euerlaſting deſtruction, but when we be well aſſayed, approoued, and
<pb facs="tcp:13277:154"/>purged with the fire of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, then let vs finiſh our courſe, and ſo well and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly fight, that we may for euermore liue with thee in that heauenly Citie, where and againſt the which, no manner temptation canpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile. Finally, graunt moſt mercifull Father, that we through thy benigne good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, may be deliuered from all euils preſent and to come both in bodie and ſoule, and that at the laſt, that yoke of
<pb facs="tcp:13277:155"/>that foule feend being ſhaken off, we may poſſeſſe the heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which thy Sonne with his precious blood bought for vs thy children: and there fore euer to haue the fruition of celeſtiall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectations, accompanied with Angels and bleſſed Saints, through the helpe, benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and grace of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, to whom, and to thee our father, and to the holy Ghoſt, be all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:13277:155"/>and honour, now and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>O Heauenly father God almightie, I pray and beſeech thy mercie beningly to behold me thy vnworthy ſeruant, that I may by thy gift of thy holy Spirit, fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently deſire thy kingdome, that I may knowne thy will and worke thereafter. Giue me O Lord wiſdome. Make me conſtant, patient and ſtrong in thee. Keepe me
<pb facs="tcp:13277:156"/>Lord from the ſleightie inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the olde wilie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Defend me from the counſailes and curſings of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill tongues, let thy mightie arme be my ſhield againſt all the malignitie of the wicked world. Remember not O Lord myne offences: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct, prepare me to repent and to be ſorie for my ſinnes. Make me to loue iuſtice, and hate wrong, to doe good, and abſtaine from all euils, that I may be worthie to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:13277:156"/>thy child. To thee be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A deuout Prayer.</head>
               <p>LORD hearken to my wordes, conſider the thought of my heart. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how lowde I crye vnto thee, let my iuſt prayer enter into thy cares, which vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly commeth from my heart. Heare me Lord, for I am poore and deſtitute of mans helpe. Take care for my Soule, ſaue me thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
<pb facs="tcp:13277:157"/>which wholy truſt in thee, haue mercie vpon me (O Lord) for I will neuer ceaſe crying to thee for helpe For thou art milde and more mercifull then any tongue can expreſſe, as often as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie aſſayleth me, I will crye and call for helpe vnto thee, I will call vpon thee in the day time, and in the night my cry ſhall not be hid from thee, O thou God of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and maker of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Lord of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:157"/>heare me a poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner calling vpon thee and putting my whole truſt in thy mercie. Haue mercie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me for thy manifold mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſake, forgiue me al myne offences. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="litany">
               <head>The Letanie.</head>
               <p>O God the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen haue mercie vpon vs miſerable ſinners.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O God the father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God the ſonne, redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of the world, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs miſerable ſinners.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:158"/>
                  <hi>O God the ſonne, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:158"/>ſpare vs good Lord, ſpare thy people, whom thou haſt redeemed with thy moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood, and be not angry with vs for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spare vs good Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From all euill and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, from ſinne, from the crafts and aſſaults of the Deuill, from thy wrath, and from euerlaſting damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From all blindneſſe of heart, from pride, vaineglo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:159"/>and hypocriſie, from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, hatred and malice, and al vucharitableneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From fornication, and all other deadly ſinne, and from all the deceits of the world, the fleſh and the deuill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord beliner vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From lightning and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, from Plague, Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Famine, from bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, and murder, and from ſudden death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:159"/>From all ſedition and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie conſpiracie, from all falſe doctrien and hereſie, from hardneſſe of heart, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thy word, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the miſterie of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incarnation, by thy holy natiuitie and circumciſion, by thy Baptiſme, faſting and temptation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By thine agonie and bloody ſweat, by thy Croſſe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:160"/>and Paſſion, by thy precious death and buriall, by thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſurrection and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by the comming of the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all time of our tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, in all time of our wealth, in the hower of death, and in the daye of iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Good Lord deliuer vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We ſinners doe beſeech thee to heare vs (O Lord God) and that it may pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:160"/>thee to rule and gouerne thy holy Church vniuerſally in the true worſhipping of thée, in righteouſneſſe and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, thy ſeruant Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth our moſt gracious Queene and gouernour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to rule her heart in thy faith, feare, and loue and that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:161"/>ſhe may euermore haue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance in thee, and euer leeke thy honour and glorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to be her defender and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, giuing her the victorie ouer all her enemies.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to illuminate all Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Church, with true knowledge and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of thy word, and that
<pb facs="tcp:13277:161"/>both by their preaching and liuing they may ſet it forth, and ſhew it accordingly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to indue the Lords of the Counſell, and all the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, with grace, wiſedome, and vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe and keepe the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, giuing them grace to execute iuſtice, and to maintaine truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:162"/>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bleſſe and keepe all thy people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to giue to all nations, vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, peace, and concord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to giue vs an heart to loue and dread thee, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to liue after thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:162"/>That it may pleaſe thee to giue all thy people in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of grace, to heare meekely thy word, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it with pure affretion, and to bring foorth the fruites of the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to bring into the way of truth, all ſuch as haue erred and are deceiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to ſtrengthen ſuch as doe
<pb facs="tcp:13277:163"/>ſtand, and to comfort and helpe the weake hearted, and to raiſe vp them that fall, and finally to beate downe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than vnder our feete.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to ſuccour, helpe, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort all that be in daunger, neceſſitie, and tribulation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to preſerue all that trauaile by land, or by water, all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men labouring of childe,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:163"/>all ſicke perſons, and young children, and to ſhew thy pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vpon all priſoners and captiues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to defend and prouide for the fatherleſſe children and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and all that be deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and oppreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee to haue mercie vpon all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:164"/>That it may pleaſe thee to giue and preſerue to our vſe, the kindlie fruites of the earth, ſo that in due time we may inioy them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may pleaſe thee, to giue vs true repentance, to forgiue vs all our ſinnes, negligences and ignorances and to indue vs with the grace of thy holy ſpirite, to amend our liues according to thy holy word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We beſeech thee, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:164"/>Sonne of God, we beſeech thee to heare vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sonne of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lambe of God, that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt away the ſinnes of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Graunt vs thy peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lambe of God that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt away the ſinnes of the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Chriſt heare vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Chriſt heare vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:165"/>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lord haue mercie vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord haue mercy vpon vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And leade vs not into temptation. But deliuer vs from euill. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The verſicle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord deale not with vs after our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither reward vs after our iniquities.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:165"/>
                  <hi>Let vs pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God mercifull father, that deſpiſeſt not the ſighing of a contrite heart, nor the deſire of ſuch as be ſorrowfull, mercifully aſſiſt our prayers that we make before thee in all our trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and aduerſities, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they oppreſſe vs, and graciouſlie heare vs, that thoſe euils which the craft and ſubteltie of the diuell, or man worketh againſt vs, be brought to naught, and by
<pb facs="tcp:13277:166"/>the prouidence of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they may be diſpearſed, that we thy ſeruants being hurt by no perſecution, may euermore giue thankes to thee in thy holy Church, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lorde ariſe, helpe vs, and deliuer vs for thy name ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God we haue heard with our eares, and our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue derlared vnto vs, the noble workes that thou
<pb facs="tcp:13277:166"/>diddeſt in their dayes, and in the olde time before them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord ariſe, helpe vs, and deliuer vs for thine honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Glorie be to the father, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>As it was in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>From our enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs O Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Graciouſly looke vpon our afflictions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pitifully beholde the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of our hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercifullie forgiue the ſins of thy people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:167"/>Fauourable with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heare our prayers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Sonne of Dauid haue mercie vpon vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both now &amp; euer vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to heare vs, O Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Graciouſlie heare vs, O Chriſt graciouſly heare vs, O Lord Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The verſicle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord let thy mercie be ſhewed vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As we do put our truſt in thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13277:167"/>
                  <hi>Let vs pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>WE humbly beſeech thee, O Father mercifully to looke vpon our infirmities, and for the glory of thy name ſake turne from vs thoſe euils that we moſt righteouſlie haue deſerued: And graunt that in all out troubles we may put our whole truſt and confidence in thy mercie, and euermore ſerue thee in holineſſe, and pureneſſe of liuing, to thy honour and glorie, through
<pb facs="tcp:13277:168"/>our onely Mediatour and Aduocate, Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer for the Queenes Maiestie.</head>
               <p>O Lord our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, high and mightie, King of Kings, Lorde of Lords, the onely ruler of Princes, which doeſt from thy throne, behold all the dwellers vpon earth, moſt hartily we beſeech thee with
<pb facs="tcp:13277:168"/>thy fauour, to beholde our moſt gracious Soueraigne Ladie Queene Elizabeth, and ſo repleniſh her with the grace of thy holy Spirite, that ſhe may alway incline to thy will, and walke in thy way, indue her plentifullie with heauenly gifts, graunt her in health and wealth long to liue, ſtrength her, that ſhe may vanquiſh and ouercome all her enemins. Adn finally after this life, ſhe may attaine euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:13277:169"/>ioy and felicitie: through Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer for Pastors and Ministers of the Church.</head>
               <p>ALmightie and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting God, which onely workeſt great meruailes, ſend downe vpon our Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Curates, and all Congregations committed to their charge, the health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:13277:169"/>ſpirit of thy grace: and that they may truely pleaſ, thee, powre vpon them the continuall dewe of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Graunt this, O Lord, for the honour of our Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and meditatour Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer of Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome.</head>
               <p>ALmightie God, which haſt giuen vs grace at this time with one accorde,
<pb facs="tcp:13277:170" rendition="simple:additions"/>to make our common ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication vnto thee, and doſt promiſe that when two or three be gatheren together in thy name, thou wilt grant their requeſtes: fulfill now, O Lord, the deſires and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions of thy ſeruants, as may be moſt expedient for them, graunting vs in this worlde knowledge of thy trueth, and in the worlde to come life euerlaſting. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:13277:170"/>
               <head>A prayer neceſſarie for all perſons.</head>
               <p>O Mercifull GOD, I a wretched ſinner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my ſelfe bound to keepe thy holy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but yet vnable to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme them, and to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for iuſt, without the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Ieſu Chriſt thy onely Sonne, who hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly fulfilled the Lawe, to iuſtifie all them that beleeue
<pb facs="tcp:13277:171"/>and truſt in him. Therefore graunt me grace, I beſeech thee, to be occupied in doing of good workes which thou commaundeſt in holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, all the dayes of my life to thy glorie, and yet to truſt onely in thy mercie, and in Chriſts merites, to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from my ſinnes, and not in my good workes, be they neuer ſo many. Giue mee grace to loue thy holy word feruently, to ſearch the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures diligentlie, to reade
<pb facs="tcp:13277:171"/>them humbly, to vnderſtand them truly, to liue after them effectuallie. Order my life ſo, O Lord, that it be alway acceptable vnto thee. Giue me grace, not to reioyce in any thing that diſpleaſeth thee, but euermore to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in thoſe things that pleaſe thee, be they neuer ſo contrarie to my deſires. Teach me ſo to pray, that my petitions may be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie heard of thee. Keepe me vpright among diuerſitie
<pb facs="tcp:13277:172"/>of opinions and iudgements in the worlde, that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſwarue from thy truth taught in holy Scripture. In proſperitie, O Lorde, ſaue me, that I waxe not proude. In aduerſitie helpe mee, that I neither diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, nor blaſpheme thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Name, but taking it pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, to giue thee thanks, and truſt to be deliuered af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy pleaſure. When I happen to fall into ſinne through frailtie, I beſeech
<pb facs="tcp:13277:172"/>thee to worke true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in my heart, that I may be ſory without deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, truſt in thy mercie without preſumption, that I may amend my life, and become truly religious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hypocriſie, lowly in hart without fayning, faithfull and truſtie without deceite, merie without lightneſſe, ſad without miſtruſt, ſober without ſlothfulneſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with mine owne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out couetouſneſſe, to tell my
<pb facs="tcp:13277:173"/>neighbour his faultes cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably without diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to inſtruct my houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde in thy Lawes truely, to obey our Queene and all gouernours vnder her vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedlie, to receiue all lawes and common ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (which diſagree not from thy holy word) obedientlie, to pay euery man that which I owe vnto him truely, to backebite no man, nor ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my neitghbour ſecretly, and to abhorre all vice, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:13277:173"/>all goodneſſe earn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly. O Lord, graunt me thus to to doe, for the glory of thy holy Name, Amen.</p>
               <p>GOd preſerue our Quéene Elizabeth, God deſtroy all her enemies, God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue her moſt honourable Counſellors.</p>
               <p>God ayde te Clergie in fetting forth of his trueth. God preſerue the Nobilitie of this Realme, and all the Commons of the ſame.
<pb facs="tcp:13277:174" rendition="simple:additions"/>God defend the fauourers of the Goſpell,. God chaunge the hearts of our enemies, and ſend them a better mind. The power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God deſtroye Autichriſt with all his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked kingdome. God ſend the Goſpell a ioyfull and free paſſage through the whole world. God ſend vnto all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees ſuch grace that they may walke worthilie in their vocation and calling. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13277:174"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
